<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><xml><records><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Abdel-Satar, Amaal M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Water quality assessment of river Nile from Idfo to Cairo</title><secondary-title>Egyptian Journal of Aquatic Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Egyptian Journal of Aquatic Research</full-title></periodical><pages>200-223</pages><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>exchangeable nutrient groups</keyword><keyword>heavy metals</keyword><keyword>major cation</keyword><keyword>nile sediment</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2005</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Abdel-Satar 2005, Nile River Sediment Quality.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Water quality of the River Nile from Idfo to Cairo and trace elements of the Nile water were seasonally investigated from autumn 2000 to summer 2001. Eleven sites were selected along the main channel of the River Nile. In addition, six stations in front of some shore-line activities were also sampled to study the man's impact on the water quality of the Nile. The distribution of major cations and anions possessed the highest values in cold seasons and the lowest during the hot high-flow period. In addition, EC, TS, TDS, COD, NH4 +, orthophosphate, total phosphorus, Fe, Mn and Cu showed a steady increase from south to north. Point and non-point sources of pollution exerted negative local effects on the water quality of the receiving waters. The multiple correlation analysis showed a pattern of interrelationships between physical and chemical parameters</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Andersson, P. S.</author><author>Porcelli, D.</author><author>Wasserburg, G. J.</author><author>Ingri, J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Particle transport of 234U-238U in the Kalix River and in the Baltic Sea</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>385-392</pages><volume>62</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1998</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0016-7037(97)00342-6</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Andersson et al. 1998, Kalix River, Swe, SPM composition &amp; U isotopes.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The role of particles for U isotope transport was investigated in the Kalix River watershed, a particle-poor, Fe/Mn-rich river in northern Sweden, and in the Baltic Sea estuary. Particles &gt;0.45μm are strongly enriched in U and contain 20-50% of the total riverine uranium budget and &lt;1% of the total U in brackish waters (3-7 PSU). The particles have high δ234U which is close to that of dissolved U in the associated water, indicating that U on particles is dominantly nondetrital and isotopically exchanges rapidly with the ambient dissolved U. Particles at the river mouth are dominated by nondetrital Fe-Mn oxyhydroxides. Uranium and Fe are strongly correlated, clearly demonstrating that secondary Fe-oxyhydroxide is the major carrier of U in river water. There is no evidence for significant association of U with Mn-oxyhydroxide. Apparent U distribution coefficients (K̂Fed) were calculated for U between the authigenic Fe on particles and the solution. These values appear to be relatively constant throughout the year. This suggests an equilibrium between Fe in solution and authigenic Fe-oxyhydroxides on detrital particles. High values of K̂Fed calculated for one summer as well as high U concentrations in brackish waters can be explained by U scavenging by biogenic phases with low authigenic Fe content. Copyright © 1998 Elsevier Science Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Andrews, M. Grace</author><author>Jacobson, Andrew D.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Controls on the solute geochemistry of subglacial discharge from the Russell Glacier, Greenland Ice Sheet determined by radiogenic and stable Sr isotope ratios</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>312-329</pages><volume>239</volume><keywords><keyword>Chemical weathering</keyword><keyword>Greenland Ice Sheet</keyword><keyword>Stable Sr isotopes</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2018</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gca.2018.08.004</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Andrews &amp; Jacobson, Russel Glacier, Greenland, Controls on solute geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2018.08.004</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>We used radiogenic and stable Sr isotope ratios (87Sr/86Sr and δ88/86Sr) to examine controls on solute acquisition in subglacial discharge from the Russell Glacier, a land-terminating lobe of the Greenland Ice Sheet (GrIS) located in western Greenland. The study focused on two melt seasons in 2014 and 2015. Subglacial discharge 87Sr/86Sr ratios are 13,000 ppm higher than those measured for bedload and suspended sediment digests, and are more similar to those of bedload sediment leachates. These results point to the preferential dissolution of minerals with high 87Sr/86Sr ratios. Analyses of mineral separates from bulk rocks demonstrate that biotite, chlorite, hornblende, and K-feldspar have relatively high 87Sr/86Sr ratios. Subglacial discharge δ88/86Sr values are ∼0.10‰ higher than those for bedload and suspended sediment digests. Isotope fractionation during secondary mineral formation and/or adsorption cannot account for the difference between subglacial discharge and bedrock δ88/86Sr values, as suspended and bedload sediment leachates and digests produced similar δ88/86Sr values and are within the range for bulk silicate Earth. Consistent with the interpretation of 87Sr/86Sr ratios, we attribute the difference to the preferential dissolution of minerals with high δ88/86Sr values. Mineral separates display a wide range of δ88/86Sr values (∼0.40‰). Those having high δ88/86Sr values include hornblende and K-feldspar, as well as apatite and titanite. Taken together, the preferential weathering of predominately silicate minerals explains the Sr isotope geochemistry of subglacial discharge. Subglacial discharge from the Russell Glacier feeds the proglacial Akuliarusiarsuup Kuua River (AKR). Along a 32 km transect of the AKR from the GrIS margin toward the coast, riverine 87Sr/86Sr ratios increase from ∼0.722 to ∼0.747 in an approximately step-wise pattern that corresponds to point-source inputs of additional subglacial discharge. Major cation concentrations and 87Sr/86Sr ratios minimally vary along lengths of the transect with no hydrological inputs. This suggests that proglacial chemical weathering is negligible and likely does not contribute significantly to GrIS solute fluxes. In general, this study supports the recent contention that silicate mineral weathering dominates the solute geochemistry of GrIS subglacial discharge in contrast to valley glaciers, which typically show substantial contributions from carbonate and sulfide weathering regardless of primary bedrock composition. Ice sheet subglacial chemical weathering may therefore have a greater impact on long-term atmospheric CO2 drawdown than previously realized.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Andrews, M. Grace</author><author>Jacobson, Andrew D.</author><author>Lehn, Gregory O.</author><author>Horton, Travis W.</author><author>Craw, Dave</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Radiogenic and stable Sr isotope ratios (87Sr/86Sr, δ88/86Sr) as tracers of riverine cation sources and biogeochemical cycling in the Milford Sound region of Fiordland, New Zealand</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>284-303</pages><volume>173</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2016</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gca.2015.10.005</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Andrews et al. 2016, Milford Sound region Fjords, New Zealand, Sediment ME, TE &amp; Sr isotopic systematics.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2015.10.005</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>This study reports radiogenic Sr isotope ratios (87Sr/86Sr), stable Sr isotope ratios (δ88/86Sr), and major ion concentrations for river, rock, sediment, soil, and plant samples collected from the Cleddau and Hollyford catchments in the Milford Sound region of Fiordland, New Zealand. The catchments primarily drain gabbro, but some tributaries access limestone and volcanogenic sediments. The goal of the study was to understand controls on riverine δ88/86Sr values in a landscape with multiple factors that may influence chemical weathering, including dense vegetation, high rainfall, and abundant, freshly-eroded Holocene fluvio-glacial and landslide debris. Rivers draining gabbro have higher δ88/86Sr values than bedrock, by as much as ~0.14‰, and the δ88/86Sr values strongly correlate with molar Ca/Sr ratios (R2=0.69). Leaching of rocks and sediment reveals no evidence for the preferential dissolution of minerals having high δ88/86Sr values and Ca/Sr ratios. In-stream Sr isotope fractionation seems unlikely because comparison against 87Sr/86Sr and Ca/Sr ratios demonstrates that riverine δ88/86Sr values conservatively trace water-mass mixing. The riverine data are best explained by the input of soil water, which is distinct from potential bedrock end-members (i.e., silicates and carbonates) based on δ88/86Sr but indistinguishable in terms of Ca/Sr and 87Sr/86Sr. While strontium isotope fractionation during secondary mineral formation and pedogenesis is possible, clay mineral formation is minor and most soils are poorly developed. Instead, soil water δ88/86Sr values more likely reflect plant uptake. Plant samples yielded a wide range of δ88/86Sr values, but on average, they are lower than those for bedrock, consistent with the expectation that plants preferentially incorporate lighter Sr isotopes. Mass-balance constraints, together with 87Sr/86Sr ratios, indicate that soil water δ88/86Sr values are ~0.30‰ higher than bedrock δ88/86Sr values, and mixing calculations show that the plant-fractionated soil water pool contributes ~27% of the riverine Sr. For tributaries accessing limestone and volcanogenic sediments, Ca/Sr and 87Sr/86Sr ratios appear consistent with two-component mixing between silicate and carbonate weathering, but δ88/86Sr values reveal a third contribution from soil water inputs, similar to gabbro catchments. The results of this study suggest that Sr isotopes behave conservatively during water mass mixing and stream transport but non-conservatively in soil, where plant uptake can elevate soil water δ88/86Sr values relative to bedrock. Plant uptake, or related biogeochemical processes, such as ion-exchange on organic matter surfaces, also appear to modify soil water Ca/Sr ratios. Many studies use 87Sr/86Sr and Ca/Sr ratios to apportion riverine solutes between silicate and carbonate weathering, but Ca/Sr ratios may be non-conservative in densely vegetated areas. The stable Sr isotope tracer shows promise for resolving riverine cation sources, as well as effects from biological cycling.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Araújo, M. F.</author><author>Valério, P.</author><author>Jouanneau, J. M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Heavy Metal Assessment in Sediments of the Ave River Basin (Portugal) by Energy-Dispersive X-Ray Fluorescence Spectrometry</title><secondary-title>X-Ray Spectrometry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>X-Ray Spectrometry</full-title></periodical><pages>305-312</pages><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1998</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/(SICI)1097-4539(199809/10)27:5&lt;305::AID-XRS275&gt;3.0.CO;2-7</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Araujo et al. 1998, Ave River, Portugal River Sediment Composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Anthropogenic activities have contaminated stream sediments around the world with toxic metals. In Portugal, the Ave river basin, draining to the northwestern Portuguese shelf, is heavily contaminated. The Ave river course and its tributaries are located in one of the most populated regions of the country with intensive agricultural and industrial activities, which effluents have been discharged directly into the local stream. This paper reports results obtained in the analysis of superficial sediments collected at the Ave estuary and along the river course within a distance of about 50 km during February 1993. In order to account for seasonal variabilities occurring in the estuary, stations located in this region were also sampled in August 1993. A total of 16 sediment samples were analysed as pressed pellets by energy-dispersive X-ray fluorescence spectrometry for 15 elements. The trend of the elemental contamination was evaluated as a function of the location, taking into account external factors that may influence that distribution (tributaries, industries, etc.) and anthropogenic contributions were identified. Comparison of our data with published values considered as the background for non-polluted sediments (average shale) were carried out by calculating enrichment factors. The latter proved that sediment contamination by Zn and Pb exists all over the river basin and also by Cr and Cu in two regions of the area studied. A general depletion in Ni was measured. No significant seasonal variabilities were detected. ©1998 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Aucour, Anne Marie</author><author>Sheppard, Simon M.F.</author><author>Guyomar, Olivier</author><author>Wattelet, Jérôme</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Use of 13C to trace origin and cycling of inorganic carbon in the Rhone river system</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>87-105</pages><volume>159</volume><issue>1-4</issue><keywords><keyword>Carbon isotope</keyword><keyword>Dissolved inorganic carbon</keyword><keyword>Global carbon cycle</keyword><keyword>Particulate inorganic carbon</keyword><keyword>Rhone river</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0009-2541(99)00035-2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://aucour1999_RhoneRiverPIC.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) and particulate inorganic carbon (PIC) were sampled at 20 sites on the Rhone and its main tributaries from Switzerland to the Mediterranean, in March, September and July (flood event) 1996. Flux estimation and DIC and PIC δ13C values are used to trace watershed inputs and fluvial processes affecting the inorganic carbon budget. DIC concentration and δ13C values vary between ~ 1 mM at -5‰ near the Rhone's source and ~ 3 mM at - 10‰ near its mouth, with tributaries draining lowland, carbonate-dominated areas at ~ 3.8 mM and - 11‰. There is an inverse relationship between river DIC concentration and DIC δ13C. The headwaters are characterized by high DIC δ13C values and low DIC, indicating a minor input of respired CO2. DIC should be mainly produced through the reaction of carbonate with atmospheric CO2 or organic/sulfuric acids. In lowland, carbonate-dominatedareas, δ13C values of ~ - 11‰ are consistent with production of DIC by weathering of limestone C (δ13C ~ -1‰) with CO2 derived from the oxidation of organic matter (δ13C ~ -21.5‰). The evolution of the Rhone's DIC concentration and δ13C appear to be largely determined by mixing between the Rhone and its main tributaries. The CO2 fluxes and DIC δ13C mass-balance, calculated for the different segments of the Rhone, point to a net, but very limited input of fluvial respired CO2 from the oxidation of organic C (&lt;5%). The PIC represents a small but quite variable fraction of the inorganic carbon (&lt;3%), except on Alpine catchments and during floods. In these cases, it can be up to 10% of the DIC concentration and export. The carbon and oxygen isotopic composition of PIC from the Rhone during a flood and from Alpine tributaries falls within the δ-range of limestones (δ13C ≥ -2‰; δ18O ≥ -6‰). Relatively light PIC isotopic composition indicate mixing of sedimentary rocks and carbonate precipitated in situ. Data for the Rhone system are typical of watersheds presenting high chemical weathering rates for HCO3, and Alpine/lowland conditions.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Bartoli, G.</author><author>Papa, S.</author><author>Sagnella, E.</author><author>Fioretto, A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Heavy metal content in sediments along the Calore river: Relationships with physical-chemical characteristics</title><secondary-title>Journal of Environmental Management</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Environmental Management</full-title></periodical><pages>S9-S14</pages><volume>95</volume><issue>SUPPL.</issue><keywords><keyword>Campania</keyword><keyword>Organic carbon</keyword><keyword>Pollution</keyword><keyword>Rivers</keyword><keyword>Sediments</keyword><keyword>Trace metals</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2012</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><accession-num>21546150</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.jenvman.2011.02.013</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Bartoli et al. 2012, Calore River, sediment OC IC N.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvman.2011.02.013</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>In the present study, trace metals contents (V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Ni, Cu, Zn, Cd and Pb) and physico-chemical parameters (nitrogen, organic and inorganic carbon, pH and particle size) in sediments samples along the Calore river were analyzed in two seasons.Sediment samples were collected in ten sites upstream and downstream of the city of Benevento and its industrial area, the confluence of Sabato and Tammaro tributaries, and the confluence of Calore and Volturno rivers. The highest contents of trace metals were found, generally, in the sites immediately downstream of industrial area and of Benevento city. The sites on the Tammaro and Sabato also showed relatively high contents of Ni and, only for Sabato sites, of Cr, and Fe. With the exception of Cd, the heavy metal contents were highest in the last site of Calore river, which therefore is a source of pollution to the Volturno river. Besides the sites downstream of Benevento city showed the higher pH values and also the highest contents of fine particles size and organic matter. Positive correlations among trace metals, organic substance, particle size sediments were found.The data obtained in this study were analyzed with reference to Interim Sediment Quality Guidelines and indicated moderate-to-high pollution by some trace metals (V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Ni, Cu). © 2011 Elsevier Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Bertassoli, Dailson J.</author><author>Sawakuchi, André O.</author><author>Sawakuchi, Henrique O.</author><author>Pupim, Fabiano N.</author><author>Hartmann, Gelvam A.</author><author>McGlue, Michael M.</author><author>Chiessi, Cristiano M.</author><author>Zabel, Matthias</author><author>Schefuß, Enno</author><author>Pereira, Tatiana S.</author><author>Santos, Rudney A.</author><author>Faustino, Samantha B.</author><author>Oliveira, Paulo E.</author><author>Bicudo, Denise C.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The fate of carbon in sediments of the Xingu and Tapajós clearwater rivers, eastern Amazon</title><secondary-title>Frontiers in Marine Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Frontiers in Marine Science</full-title></periodical><volume>4</volume><issue>FEB</issue><keywords><keyword>Amazon</keyword><keyword>Carbon Cycle</keyword><keyword>Greenhouse gases</keyword><keyword>Tapajós River</keyword><keyword>Xingu River</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.3389/fmars.2017.00044</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://bertassoli2017.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The Xingu and Tapajós rivers in the eastern Amazon are the largest clearwater systems of the Amazon basin. Both rivers have &quot;fluvial rias&quot; (i.e., lake-like channels) in their downstream reaches as they are naturally impounded by the Amazon mainstem. Fluvial rias are widespread in the Amazon landscape and most of the sedimentary load from the major clearwater and blackwater rivers is deposited in these channels. So far, little is known about the role of Amazon rias as a trap and reactor for organic sediments. In this study, we used organic and inorganic geochemistry, magnetic susceptibility, diatom, and pollen analyses in sediments (suspended, riverbed, and downcore) of the Xingu and Tapajós rias to investigate the effects of hydrologic variations on the carbon budget in these clearwater rivers over the Holocene. Ages of sediment deposition (~100 to 5,500 years) were constrained by optically stimulated luminescence and radiocarbon. Major elements geochemistry and concentration of total organic carbon (TOC) indicate that seasonal hydrologic variations exert a strong influence on riverine productivity and on the input and preservation of organic matter in sediments. Stable carbon isotope data (δ13C from -31.04 to -27.49‰) and pollen analysis indicate that most of the carbon buried in rias is derived from forests. In the Xingu River, diatom analysis in bottom sediments revealed 65 infrageneric taxa that are mostly well-adapted to slack oligotrophic and acidic waters. TOC values in sediment cores are similar to values measured in riverbed sediments and indicate suitable conditions for organic matter preservation in sediments of the Xingu and Tapajós rias at least since the mid-Holocene, with carbon burial rates varying from about 84 g m-2 yr-1 to 169 g m-2 yr-1. However, redox-sensitive elements in sediment core indicate alternation between anoxic/dysoxic and oxic conditions in the water-sediment interface that may be linked to abrupt changes in precipitation. The variation between anoxic/dysoxic and oxic conditions in the water-sediment interface controls organic matter mineralization and methanogenesis. Thus, such changes promoted by hydrological variations significantly affect the capacity of Amazon rias to act either as sources or sinks of carbon.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Borges, Joniell B.</author><author>Huh, Youngsook</author><author>Moon, Seulgi</author><author>Noh, Hyeonjeong</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Provenance and weathering control on river bed sediments of the eastern Tibetan Plateau and the Russian Far East</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>52-72</pages><volume>254</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>CIA</keyword><keyword>Chang Jiang (Yangtze)</keyword><keyword>Hong (Red)</keyword><keyword>Lena</keyword><keyword>Mekong</keyword><keyword>Salween</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2008</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2008.06.002</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Borges et al. 2008, Tibet Plateau and Russian far east rivers sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We investigated the petrography and major, trace and rare earth element compositions of the bed sediments from the large rivers draining the eastern Tibetan Plateau (ETP) - the Huang He (Yellow), Chang Jiang (Yangtze), Hong He (Red), Mekong and Salween. The combined drainage spans tropical, temperate and arid climate zones. In addition, samples from the Lena River, draining the Verkhoyansk and Sette-Daban ranges in an arctic to sub-arctic climate zone in Siberia, were also studied for their major and trace element composition. The sub-angular texture, the quartz:feldspar:rock fragment classification in the lithic arenite field, and the relatively low chemical index of alteration (CIA: 42-79), indicate that these sediments are texturally, petrographically and chemically immature, and immobile trace elements can be used to obtain some information about the lithologic provenance. The ETP river sediments are felsic and similar to the Upper Continental Crust, with the Salween most felsic and the Lena most mafic. The sediments show a gradation in maturity that is not clearly related to present climatic or physiographic regime. This suggests that maturity itself is a relict feature inherited from previous sedimentary cycles. The high physical erosion in such high energy and relief systems seems to inhibit intense weathering and manifests a provenance control from local rocks on the sediment compositions. © 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Canfield, Donald E.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The geochemistry of river particulates from the continental USA: Major elements</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>3349-3365</pages><volume>61</volume><issue>16</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1997</year></dates><accession-num>11540476</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0016-7037(97)00172-5</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Canfield, 1997, USA continental river particulate geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>River particulates have been collected from twenty-three rivers from throughout the continental USA. The rivers drain mostly large basins (basin areas range from 2.1 × 103 to 2970 × 103 km2) composed of mixed lithologies, and spanning a wide range of climatic conditions as evidenced by a large variation in air and ground water temperatures, precipitation, and runoff. Suspended particulates have been analyzed for organic and inorganic carbon, as well as the major elements Al, Fe, Mn, K, Si, Ca, Mg, and Na. Also determined were suspended sediment loads at the time of sampling, particle surface areas, and grain size distributions. Five-year average river water chemistry and suspended sediment concentrations, obtained from USGS water supply reports, are also included as supporting information. Particle chemistry systematically varies with rates of runoff, with high runoff rivers transporting the most heavily altered particulates and low runoff rivers carrying the least altered. Degrees of alteration are indicated by the extent to which the refractory, nonmobile elements Al and Fe are concentrated into the particulates and the extent to which the most easily weathered elements Na, Ca, and Mg have been leached. Overall, the susceptibility of elements towards leaching is consistent with numerous previous descriptions of element mobility on weathering. A simple predictive model has been developed to explore and explain the observed trends between particle composition and river runoff. Thus, the elemental composition of riverine particulates may be given by the expression PCOi = [(Propi)TM-DCOi]/SS, where PCOi is the concentration of element i (as the oxide) in a riverine particulate, Prop, is the proportion of i (as the oxide) in unweathered rock, DCO, is the dissolved concentration of i (as the equivalent oxide), TM is the total rock derived mass dissolved in river water, and SS is suspended sediment concentration. To utilize this equation, a model was first developed to predict the concentration of river solutes with the input of temperature, precipitation, and a limited number of weathering parameters. Combining this solute model with the above predictive equation for particle composition, it was discovered that the observed trends between particle composition and runoff require the special circumstance of decreasing SS with increasing runoff. Hence, the composition of river particulates depends both on the climate parameters of runoff and temperature (as they control dissolved river chemistry) and the nonclimate parameters including elevation, relief, tectonics, and basin area that control the SS load of rivers. Copyright © 1997 Elsevier Science Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Chakrapani, G. J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Major and trace element geochemistry in upper Ganga river in the Himalayas, India</title><secondary-title>Environmental Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environmental Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>189-201</pages><volume>48</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Himalayas</keyword><keyword>Major elements</keyword><keyword>Trace elements Ganga River</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2005</year></dates><isbn>9113322850</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s00254-005-1287-1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Chakrapani2005_Upr Ganga Min+AqChem.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Chemical weathering and resulting water compositions in the upper Ganga river in the Himalayas were studied. For the first time, temporal and spatial sampling for a 1 year period (monthly intervals) was carried out and analyzed for dissolved major elements, trace elements, Rare Earth Elements (REE), and strontium isotopic compositions. Amounts of physical and chemical loads show large seasonal variations and the overall physical load dominates over chemical load by a factor of more than three. The dominant physical weathering is also reflected in high quartz and illite/mica contents in suspended sediments. Large seasonal variations also occur in major elemental concentrations. The water type is categorized as HCO 3- -SO 42- -Ca2+ dominant, which constitute &gt;60% of the total water composition. On an average, only about 5-12% of HCO 3- is derived from silicate lithology, indicating the predominance of carbonate lithology in water chemistry in the head waters of the Ganga river. More than 80% Na+ and K+ are derived from silicate lithology. The silicate lithology is responsible for the release of low Sr with extremely radiogenic Sr (87Sr/86 Sr&gt;0.75) in Bhagirathi at Devprayag. However, there is evidence for other end-member lithologies for Sr other than carbonate and silicate lithology. Trace elements concentrations do not indicate any pollution, although presence of arsenic could be a cause for concern. High uranium mobilization from silicate rocks is also observed. The ∑ REE is much less compared to other major world rivers such as the Amazon, perhaps because in the present study, only samples filtered through &lt;0.2 μm were analysed. Negative Eu anomalies in suspended sediments is due to the excess carbonate rock weathering in the source area. © Springer-Verlag 2005.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Chen, Jingsheng</author><author>Wang, Feiyue</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Chemical composition of river particulates in eastern China</title><secondary-title>GeoJournal</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>GeoJournal</full-title></periodical><pages>31-37</pages><volume>40</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1996</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/BF00222528</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Chen &amp; Wang 1996_Eastern China River Sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A total of 42 aquatic particulate samples (suspended matter and &lt; 63 μm surficial sediments) was collected from 11 large rivers in eastern China. Contents of both major elements (Al, Si, Ca, Mg, K, Na, Ti, Fe, Mn) and trace elements (Cu, Pb, Zn, Cd, Cr, Co, Ni, V) in the particulate samples were analyzed. The geographic variations of river particulate compositions were studied. The results showed that the Yellow River particulates contained a notably high content of Ca and a low content of Al. Except for the Yellow River, Al contents in particulates increased from the northern rivers to the southern rivers, while K and Na decreased. Trace elements were relatively enriched in the southern river particulates. The geographic variations seemed to be related to the weathering types and geological background within the river basins. The average composition of river particulates in China was then estimated. Based on the Chinese river data from this paper, as well as on the literature data for other main world rivers, a new estimation of the global average particulate composition was reported. Since the earlier estimations in the literature were not concerned with or at best concerned only with few of the Chinese rivers which contribute a major proportion to the global load of river particulates, this new estimation may be more reasonable.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Chetelat, B.</author><author>Liu, C. Q.</author><author>Gaillardet, J.</author><author>Wang, Q. L.</author><author>Zhao, Z. Q.</author><author>Liang, C. S.</author><author>Xiao, Y. K.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Boron isotopes geochemistry of the Changjiang basin rivers</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>6084-6097</pages><volume>73</volume><issue>20</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2009</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gca.2009.07.026</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Chetalat et al. 2009, Chanjiang River Boron isotopes.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2009.07.026</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>We report analyses of B isotopic compositions in water and suspended particulate matter collected in the Changjiang and its main tributaries. We showed that four sources control the dissolved boron budget; namely atmospheric deposition, evaporite dissolution, anthropogenic inputs and silicate weathering. The contribution of silicate weathering to the dissolved B load ranges from 40% to 50% for the Changjiang main channel and from 45% to 88% for the main tributaries. The isotopic composition of dissolved boron derived from silicate weathering range from -3‰ up to +9‰ suggesting that isotopic fractionation occurs during silicate weathering. The boron isotopic composition of suspended particulate matter range from -11.4‰ to -6‰. Boron derived from silicate weathering is preferentially carried out by the dissolved load which accounts for 30-96% of the total boron. We show that the isotopic compositions of both the dissolved load and suspended particulate matter are controlled by the competition between boron leaching and boron uptake into secondary phases. The first process is characterized by a loss of boron relative to the bedrock without apparent isotopic fractionation whereas the last one is associated to a large isotopic fractionation which enriches the dissolved boron in heavy isotope. © 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Chetelat, Benjamin</author><author>Liu, Conq Qiang</author><author>Wang, Qilian</author><author>Zhang, Guoping</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Assessing the influence of lithology on weathering indices of Changjiang river sediments</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>108-115</pages><volume>359</volume><keywords><keyword>Changjiang basin</keyword><keyword>Climate</keyword><keyword>Lithologic control</keyword><keyword>Suspended sediments</keyword><keyword>Weathering indices</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2013.09.018</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Chetelat et al.2013_ChangjianRiver China.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2013.09.018</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>We present major and trace element data in suspended particulate matter (SPM) collected in the Changjiang main channel and its tributaries. Suspended sediments are derived from a mafic source related to the Emeishan Large Igneous Province (ELIP) in the Upper Reach and from a more felsic source in the Middle/Lower Reaches. The difference in chemical composition between the two sources has a strong influence on the apparent weathering intensity. Although the apparent loss of soluble elements follows a climatic gradient from the Upper Reach to the Lower Reach, the co-variation of weathering indices with different proxies for igneous differentiation suggests that a lithologic control cannot be ruled out. By taking into account the variability in chemical composition of the parent rocks, we show that river suspended sediments from the upper reach may have not experienced less intense chemical weathering than those transported by rivers from the Lower/Middle Reaches characterized by higher runoff and surface temperature. We argue that the relationships observed for different indices of weathering with climate are probably an artifact and are mainly driven by the change in chemical composition of the sediment's parent-rocks. © 2013 Elsevier B.V.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Churchman, G.J.</author><author>Hunt, J.L.</author><author>Glasby, G.P.</author><author>R.M., Renner.</author><author>Griffiths, G.A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Input of river-derived sediment to the New Zealand continental shelf: II Mineralogy and Composition</title><secondary-title>Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science</full-title></periodical><pages>397-411</pages><volume>27</volume><keywords><keyword>New Zealand</keyword><keyword>continental shelf</keyword><keyword>rivers</keyword><keyword>sediments</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1988</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://churchman1988_NewZealand river SPM ClayMin and chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The input of river-borne sediments to the New Zealand continental shelf has been calculated for all the major rivers and basins in New Zealand. South Island yields 284 ± 40 × 106 tonnes per year of sediment from a land area of 152 977 km2 and North Island yields 105 ± 9·4 × 106 tonnes per year from a land area of 114 621 km2. Particularly high discharges are noted off the west coast of South Island and east coast of North Island and result in higher offshore sedimentation there. The data are compatible with measured sedimentation rates on the New Zealand continental shelf. The specific sediment yield from South Island is amongst the highest previously recorded. © 1985.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Clark, Kathryn E</author><author>Shanley, James B</author><author>Scholl, Martha A</author><author>Perdrial, Nicolas</author><author>Plante, Alain F</author><author>Mcdowell, William H</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Tropical river suspended sediment and solute dynamics in storms during an extreme drought</title><secondary-title>Water Resources Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Resources Research</full-title></periodical><pages>3695-3712</pages><volume>53</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2017</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/2016WR019737.</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://clark et al. 2017, SPM puerto rico (2).pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Compton, John S.</author><author>Maake, Livhuwani</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Source of the suspended load of the upper Orange River, South Africa</title><secondary-title>South African Journal of Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>South African Journal of Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>339-348</pages><volume>110</volume><issue>2-3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2007</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.2113/gssajg.110.2-3.339</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Compton &amp; Maake 2007, Upr Orange Rivery, Source_of_the_suspended_load.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The Orange River is one of the World's most turbid; delivering 60 million tons of sediment each year to the western margin of South Africa. Much of this sediment is believed to be from soil erosion, an increasing environmental threat to sustainability in southern Africa. This study focuses on the upper reaches of the Orange River above the Caledon River confluence, because it is here that high rainfall and topographic relief of the Drakensberg Mountains produce most of the Orange River's suspended load. Comparison of grain size, mineralogy and geochemistry of the suspended sediment load with catchment bedrock soils provides an estimate of the source of the suspended sediment. Major and trace element ratios indicate that the suspended sediment load is primarily derived from Karoo (upper Beaufort and Stormberg groups) sedimentary rocks rather than Drakensberg basalt. The Caledon River carries the largest fine-mud suspended load primarily from the erosion of Karoo sedimentary rock soils. The organic carbon content of the suspended load ranges from 1.0 to 1.3 weight % with δ 13C values that range from -19.7 to - 16.9‰ PDB. The δ13C values of the organic fraction of soils is highly variable (-21.5 to -12.7‰ PDB) and reflect the mix of C3 and C4 vegetation in the catchment area. © 2007 September Geological Society of South Africa.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dalai, T.K.</author><author>Krishnaswami, S.</author><author>Sarin, M.M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Major ion chemistry in the headwaters of the Yamuna river system:</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>3397-3416</pages><volume>66</volume><issue>19</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2002</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/s0016-7037(02)00937-7</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dalai et al. 2002, Yanuma river major ion chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The Yamuna river and its tributaries in the Himalaya constitute the Yamuna River System (YRS). The YRS basin has a drainage area and discharge comparable in magnitude to those of the Bhagirathi and the Alaknanda rivers, which merge to form the Ganga at the foothills of the Himalaya. A detailed geochemical study of the YRS was carried out to determine: (i) the relative significance of silicate, carbonate and evaporite weathering in contributing to its major ion composition; (ii) CO2 consumption via silicate weathering; and (iii) the factors regulating chemical weathering of silicates in the basin. The results show that the YRS waters are mildly alkaline, with a wide range of TDS, ∼32 to ∼620 mg l−1. In these waters, the abundances of Ca, Mg and alkalinity, which account for most of TDS, are derived mainly from carbonates. Many of the tributaries in the lower reaches of the Yamuna basin are supersaturated with calcite. In addition to carbonic acid, sulphuric acid generated by oxidation of pyrites also seems to be supplying protons for chemical weathering. Silicate weathering in YRS basin contributes, on average, ∼25% (molar basis) of total cations on a basin wide scale. Silicate weathering, however, does not seem to be intense in the basin as evident from low Si/(Na*+K) in the waters, ∼1.2 and low values of chemical index of alteration (CIA) in bed sediments, ∼60. CO2 drawdown resulting from silicate weathering in the YRS basin in the Himalaya during monsoon ranges between (4 to 7) × 105 moles km−2 y−1. This is higher than that estimated for the Ganga at Rishikesh for the same season. The CO2 consumption rates in the Yamuna and the Ganga basins in the Himalaya are higher than the global average value, suggesting enhanced CO2 drawdown in the southern slopes of the Himalaya. The impact of this enhanced drawdown on the global CO2 budget may not be pronounced, as the drainage area of the YRS and the Ganga in the Himalaya is small. The CO2 drawdown by silicates in the YRS basin is marginally higher than the reported values of CO2 release from oxidation of organic rich sediments, estimated using Re as a proxy. This comparison shows the need to constrain CO2 sources and sinks better to balance its budget in a regional scale. The results also show that silicate weathering rate in the YRS basin is ∼10 mm ky−1 and on the Ganga basin, it is ∼5 mm ky−1, which are several times lower than the carbonate weathering rates. The significantly higher silicate weathering rate observed in the YRS basin seems to be governed by rapid physical erosion in this region. The apparent activation energy for overall silicate weathering in the YRS basin, derived from Na* and Si concentrations and water temperature, ranges from ∼50 to 80 kJ mol−1. These values are comparable to those reported for granitoid weathering in natural watersheds and feldspar weathering in laboratory experiments. This study brings to light the sources contributing to major ions, enhanced chemical weathering rates in the Yamuna River Basin and interdependence of silicate weathering on physical erosion and temperature.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dalai, Tarun K.</author><author>Krishnaswami, S.</author><author>Sarin, M. M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Barium in the Yamuna River System in the Himalaya: Sources, fluxes, and its behavior during weathering and transport</title><secondary-title>Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</full-title></periodical><pages>1-23</pages><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><keywords><keyword>dissolved ba</keyword><keyword>himalaya</keyword><keyword>weathering</keyword><keyword>yamuna river</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2002</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2002gc000381</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dalai et al. 2002b, Yanuma River, Ba.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>[1] Systematic measurements of Ba in waters and bed sediments of the Yamuna and many of its tributaries in the Himalaya (Yamuna River System) have been carried out. Dissolved Ba in the Yamuna River System (YRS) ranges from 17 to 871 nM. Streams near the source region draining predominantly granites/gneisses have lower abundance of Ba, &lt;100 nM compared with those in the lower reaches. These data, coupled with those available for major ion composition of these rivers and their sediments, have been used to determine the contributions of silicates and carbonates, the two major lithologies in the drainage basin, to dissolved Ba in YRS. In YRS, dissolved Ba shows significant covariations with Na*, Si, Ca, and Mg. Using Na* as an index, it is estimated that silicates are an important source of Ba to many of the rivers; in a few streams in the lower reaches, however, they account for only &lt;20% of measured Ba. Carbonate weathering, which dominates the major ion composition of YRS rivers, contributes on average similar to30% of dissolved Ba. Together, silicates and carbonates roughly balance measured Ba in many of the rivers, whereas in a few streams, Ba contributions from additional sources are needed to balance the budget. Prospective sources include organic matter/phosphorites. Plot of 1/Ba versus Sr-87/Sr-86 shows a two-component mixing trend, one with low Ba-high Sr-87/Sr-86 (silicates) and the other with high Ba-low Sr-87/Sr-86 (carbonates, phosphorites). Ba also shows significant positive correlation with dissolved Re and SO4. A likely explanation for the Ba-Re-SO4 association is that they are supplied from organic matter/phosphorites/ carbonates assemblages through H2SO4 weathering. In YRS bed sediments, Ba shows significant correlation with K and Al. Ba/ Na and Ba/Sr in these sediments are higher than those in granites of the Higher Himalaya. These observations can be explained in terms of (1) differential release of these elements during weathering, Ba being less mobile because of its association with weathering resistant minerals or (2) &quot;nonconservative'' behavior of Ba in rivers resulting in its removal from dissolved to particulate phases. Either way, these results indicate that Ba is less mobile relative to Na and Sr. Dissolved Ba flux from the YRS basin is 5 times more than that from the Ganga headwaters, a result consistent with higher physical and chemical erosion in the YRS basin. The Yamuna and the Ganga together transport similar to5.4 x 10(6) mol yr(-1) of Ba out of the Himalaya, which is similar to10% of the dissolved Ba flux from the Ganga at Bangladesh, roughly the same as their contribution to water discharge. The rate of Ba mobilization in the Yamuna and the Ganga basins in the Himalaya is a factor of similar to2 higher than the global average</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dalai, Tarun K.</author><author>Rengarajan, R.</author><author>Patel, P. P.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sediment geochemistry of the Yamuna River System in the Himalaya: Implications to weathering and transport</title><secondary-title>Geochemical Journal</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochemical Journal</full-title></periodical><pages>441-453</pages><volume>38</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords><keyword>Chemical weathering</keyword><keyword>Elemental mobility</keyword><keyword>Himalaya</keyword><keyword>Sediment chemistry</keyword><keyword>Yamuna River</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.2343/geochemj.38.441</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dalai et al. 2004, Yanuma River, Ganges Trib, Sediment ME.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Bed sediments of the Yamuna River and its tributaries in the Himalaya (Yamuna River System, YRS) have been anlyzed for major elements and trace metals (Sr, Ba, Ni, Cu, Co, Zn, Pb and Cr). These results have been used to characterize chemical weathering and transport in the Himalaya, to assess relative mobility of elements during weathering and to understand heavy metal association. Concentrations of major and trace elements of YRS sediments vary between 20 and 50%. In general, elemental variability reduces when data are analyzed individually for the major rivers, suggesting that tributaries draining diverse lithology contribute significant variations. Comparison of sediment chemistry with composition of source rocks and average Upper Continental Crust (UCC) suggests significant loss of Na, K, Ca and Mg from source rocks during weathering, the degree of loss being more for Ca and Na. Chemical index of alteration (CIA) for YRS sediments averages at 59, indicating that weathering in the basin is of moderate intensity. This inference is also supported by major ion chemistry of YRS waters and is attributed to steep gradient and enhanced physical erosion in the basin. Available results seem to indicate that Na and Sr are effectively more mobile than Ba, which is thought to be a combined effect of higher solubility of Na and Sr, and the affinity of Ba to be adsorbed onto solid phase. Heavy metals show significant positive correlation with Al and weak correlation with Fe, Mn and P. These observations suggest that metal concentrations are controlled mainly by clay mineral abundances, and that Fe-Mn oxides and organic matter may be playing less significant role. Heavy metal concentrations of YRS sediments are lower than those of suspended particulates of the Yamuna river, presumably due to higher clay mineral abundances in the latter. Strong association of metals with Al, and lower metal concentrations in bed sediments compared to suspended matter underscores the importance of sediment transport and mineral sorting in influencing the YRS sediment chemistry. Enrichment factor and geo-accumulation index calculated for heavy metals in YRS sediments suggest that they are mainly of natural origin and that anthropogenic activities exert little influence on their abundances. Copyright © 2004 by The Geochemical Society of Japan.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Davide, Vignati</author><author>Pardos, Michel</author><author>Diserens, Jérôme</author><author>Ugazio, Giancarlo</author><author>Thomas, Richard</author><author>Dominik, Janusz</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Characterisation of bed sediments and suspension of the river Po (Italy) during normal and high flow conditions</title><secondary-title>Water Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Research</full-title></periodical><pages>2847-2864</pages><volume>37</volume><issue>12</issue><keywords><keyword>KD</keyword><keyword>Nutrients</keyword><keyword>River Po</keyword><keyword>River hydrology</keyword><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>Trace metals</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><accession-num>12767288</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0043-1354(03)00133-7</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Davide et al. 2003, Po river sediment characterisation, normal and high flow.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Grain-size distribution, major elements, nutrients and trace metals were determined in bed sediments and suspension collected at 10 representative sites along the river Po under normal and high flow conditions. Grain-size distribution and major element composition of suspension highlighted the presence of two distinct particle populations in the upper-middle Po (coarser particles, lower carbonate content) and in the lower Po (finer particles, higher carbonate content). This change partly reflects the geological differences between the two parts of the basin, and also the presence of a hydroelectric power plant at Isola Serafini (Piacenza). With respect to environmental quality issues, bed sediments and suspension provide similar results. A moderate nutrient pollution is found in all but the uppermost parts of the river basin, while the most significant inputs of trace metals appear to originate from the urban areas of Turin and Milan. Calculation of sediment enrichment factors identifies Cd, Cu, Hg and Zn as the most impacted elements by human activities. On the other hand, the high levels of Ni and Cr throughout the river seem to derive mainly from the presence of basic rocks in the upper and middle parts of the basin. Both nutrient and trace metal particulate concentrations substantially decrease under high flow conditions possibly due to &quot;flushing&quot; of contaminated bed sediments and resuspension of coarser material. Under normal flow conditions, water hydrochemistry and concentrations of some elements (As, Ca, Cr, Cu, K, Mg, Mn, Na, Ni, and Pb) in the dissolved phase (&lt;0.45μm) were also determined. Calculation of trace metals partition coefficients shows that the relative importance of the particulate and water phases varies in response to water hydrochemistry and suspended solid content, but that most elements achieve a conditional equilibrium in the lower stretches of the river Po. These results are the first of this kind reported for the whole river course and highlight the factors and mechanisms controlling the origin, mobility and fate of nutrients and trace metals in the river Po. © 2003 Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Depetris, Pedro J.</author><author>Probst, Jean Luc</author><author>Pasquini, Andrea I.</author><author>Gaiero, Diego M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The geochemical characteristics of the Paraná River suspended sediment load: An initial assessment</title><secondary-title>Hydrological Processes</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Hydrological Processes</full-title></periodical><pages>1267-1277</pages><volume>17</volume><issue>7</issue><keywords><keyword>CIA</keyword><keyword>Geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Paraná River</keyword><keyword>REE</keyword><keyword>Sediment sources</keyword><keyword>Suspended sediment</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/hyp.1283</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://depetris2003_Parana&amp;Uruguay river SPM chemistry_V.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Most water in the Paraná River drainage basin is supplied by the tropical Upper Paraná (over 60% of the total annual water discharge, 550 km3). The total suspended solids (TSS) load (c. 80 × 106 t year-1), however, is essentially furnished (50-70%) by the mountainous, arid and mostly sediment-mantled upper Bermejo River drainage basin. This characteristic suggests that the Paraná River solid load (TSS, 600 km upstream from the mouth) is largely recycled sedimentary material, whose discharge-weighted mean chemical index of alteration is c. 71. The extended UCC-normalized multi-elemental diagrams are similar to those of other world rivers. Nevertheless, the detailed inspection of UCC-normalized rare earth element (REE) 'spidergrams' reveals a lithological source for the Paraná River TSS that might be compatible with either tholeiitic flood basalts (widespread in the upper drainage) or with young Andean intermediate volcanic rocks. In view of the Bermejo River's dominant role as a sediment contributor, we feel that the signature preserved in the Paraná's TSS is the latter. Conversely, the Uruguay River TSS REE signature is certainly determined by the extensive weathering products of Jurassic-Cretaceous tholeiitic basalts. © 2003 John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dinis, Pedro A.</author><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Hahn, Annette</author><author>Vermeesch, Pieter</author><author>Cabral-Pinto, Marina</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Weathering indices as climate proxies. A step forward based on Congo and SW African river muds</title><secondary-title>Earth-Science Reviews</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth-Science Reviews</full-title></periodical><pages>103039</pages><volume>201</volume><issue>November 2019</issue><keywords><keyword>Chemical weathering</keyword><keyword>Climate</keyword><keyword>Congo</keyword><keyword>Mud composition</keyword><keyword>Rainfall proxies</keyword><keyword>SW African margin</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.earscirev.2019.103039</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dinis et al. 2020, Congo river mud Weathering indices, clay mineralogy and chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2019.103039</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Despite the influence of other geological and geomorphological factors, chemical weathering at the Earth's surface is strongly controlled by climate. Thus, a measure of weathering intensity determined from soils or sediments should provide information about the climatic conditions associated with their formation. Available geochemical and mineralogical data on modern fluvial and marine muds from different regions of southern Africa and its Atlantic continental margin are used to review the links between sediment composition and climatic properties together with the possible causes of variance. Although river muds may not be generated exclusively in a single sedimentary cycle and erosion and weathering processes do not necessarily take place in a spatially homogeneous way, significant relationships between mineralogical and geochemical signatures of river mud and rainfall in the corresponding catchment area were recognised. Our study shows that the composition of clay is strongly influenced by climatically-driven weathering, whilst coarser mud fractions tend to be more affected by provenance, grain size, hydraulic sorting, and recycling. In the marine environment the climatic signal may be lost even in clay, because of hydraulic fractionation, authigenic mineral growth and mixing with foreign particles. Given the ubiquitous character of fluvial muds, and the easy and non-expensive methods available for separating and analysing clay fractions, their geochemical fingerprints represent a most precious source of information concerning climate. Any geochemical parameter used as a regional proxy of climate, however, still requires that the diversity of geological, geomorphological, and biological factors that affect its value are cautiously considered.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Dornblaser, Mark M.</author><author>Striegl, Robert G.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Suspended sediment and carbonate transport in the Yukon River Basin, Alaska: Fluxes and potential future responses to climate change</title><secondary-title>Water Resources Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Resources Research</full-title></periodical><volume>45</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords><keyword>http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2008WR007546, doi:10.102</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2009</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2008WR007546</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Dornblaser&amp;Striegl, 2009, Yukon river SPM and carbonate transport.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Loads and yields of suspended sediment and carbonate were measured and modeled at three locations on the Yukon, Tanana, and Porcupine Rivers in Alaska during water years 2001-2005 (1 October 2000 to 30 September 2005). Annual export of suspended sediment and carbonate upstream from the Yukon Delta averaged 68 Mt a-1 and 387 Gg a-1, respectively, with 50% of the suspended sediment load originating in the Tanana River Basin and 88% of the carbonate load originating in the White River Basin. About half the annual suspended sediment export occurred during spring, and half occurred during summer-autumn, with very little export in winter. On average, a minimum of 11 Mt a-1 of suspended sediment is deposited in floodplains between Eagle, Alaska, and Pilot Station, Alaska, on an annual basis, mostly in the Yukon Flats. There is about a 27% loss in the carbonate load between Eagle and Yukon River near Stevens Village, with an additional loss of about 29% between Stevens Village and Pilot Station, owing to a combination of deposition and dissolution. Comparison of current and historical suspended sediment loads for Tanana River suggests a possible link between suspended sediment yield and the Pacific decadal oscillation.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Douglas, G. B.</author><author>Hart, B. T.</author><author>Beckett, R.</author><author>Gray, C. M.</author><author>Oliver, R. L.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of suspended particulate matter (SPM) in the Murray-Darling River system: A conceptual isotopic/geochemical model for the fractionation of major, trace and rare earth elements</title><secondary-title>Aquatic Geochemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Aquatic Geochemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>167-194</pages><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Colloid</keyword><keyword>Fractionation</keyword><keyword>Murray-Darling River system</keyword><keyword>Particulate</keyword><keyword>Sr isotope</keyword><keyword>Suspended particulate matter</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1023/A:1009632310689</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://douglas et al. 1999_Murray-Darling River, Eastern Australia, SPM ME, TE &amp; REE.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A conceptual isotopic/geochemical model is presented to explain the variation of major, trace and rare earth element (REE) geochemistry and Sr isotope systematics in suspended particulate matter (SPM) as a function of particle/colloid size. This conceptual model is an extension of a previous investigation of the origin of SPM in the Murray-Darling River system (MDRS) has utilised Sr isotope systematics to examine aspects of SPM (particle/colloid) origin, structure and mineralogy. The geochemical processes that give rise to the often coherent trends in major, trace and REE geochemistry and Sr isotopic signature as a function of particulate (&gt;1 μm) and colloidal (&lt;1 μm) size in the MDRS have been identified using an enhanced SPM size fractionation technique as a basis to not only obtain a broad range of particle/colloid size ranges, but also to provide sufficient material for subsequent geochemical and isotopic analysis. The conceptual isotopic/geochemical model proposed here contains three major components: (i) the differential weathering of micas and alkali (K-) feldspars to form the majority of the particulate (&gt;1 μm) fractions (high 87Sr/86Sr ratio), which have a geochemical and Sr isotopic signature that closely resembles precursor mineralogies, (ii) the differential weathering of Na, Ca-feldspars (plagioclase) which decompose to form clay minerals in the colloidal (&lt;1 μm) fractions (low 87Sr/86Sr ratio), with a range of geochemical signatures related to the relative proportions of inorganic and organic constituents, and (iii) the presence of natural organic matter as coatings on the particulate (&gt;1 μm) and colloidal (&lt;1 μm) matter and possibly as organo-colloids which exert an increasing influence in particular on bulk colloid geochemistry with decreasing colloid size. This conceptual isotopic/geochemical model also accounts for the distinct variation in major, trace and REE geochemistry and Sr isotopic systematics between the particulate (&gt;1 μm) and colloidal (&lt;1 μm) fractions, the variation being primarily a function of the distinctly different precursor mineralogies of the SPM fractions and geochemical fractionation during the weathering and transport. Additionally, this model explains a systematic fractionation of REE apparent within colloidal (&lt;1 μm) fractions. Statistical (hierachical cluster) analysis of two particulate and three colloidal fractions from 23 samples from the MDRS is used as a basis to investigate geochemical and mineralogical associations within the particulate and colloidal size fractions and to provide additional supporting evidence for the conceptual isotopic/geochemical model.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Eberl, D. D.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Quantitative mineralogy of the Yukon River system: Changes with reach and season, and determining sediment provenance</title><secondary-title>American Mineralogist</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>American Mineralogist</full-title></periodical><pages>1784-1794</pages><volume>89</volume><issue>11-12</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.2138/am-2004-11-1225</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://eberl2004, Yukon River, quantitative mineralogy.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The mineralogy of Yukon River basin sediment has been studied by quantitative X-ray diffraction. Bed, beach, bar, and suspended sediments were analyzed using the RockJock computer program. The bed sediments were collected from the main stem and from selected tributaries during a single trip down river, from Whitehorse to the Yukon River delta, during the summer of 2001. Beach and bar sediments were collected from the confluence region of the Tanana and Yukon Rivers during the summer of 2003. Suspended sediments were collected at three stations on the Yukon River and from a single station on the Tanana River at various times during the summers of 2001 through 2003, with the most complete set of samples collected during the summer of 2002. Changes in mineralogy of Yukon River bed sediments are related to sediment dilution or concentration effects from tributary sediment and to chemical weathering during transport. Carbonate minerals compose about 2 wt% of the bed sediments near Whitehorse, but increase to 14 wt% with the entry of the White River tributary above Dawson. Thereafter, the proportion of carbonate minerals decreases downstream to values of about 1 to 7 wt% near the mouth of the Yukon River. Quartz and feldspar contents of bed sediments vary greatly with the introduction of Pelly River and White River sediments, but thereafter either increase irregularly (quartz from 20 to about 50 wt%) or remain relatively constant (feldspar at about 35 wt%) with distance downstream. Clay mineral content increases irregularly downstream from about 15 to about 30 wt%. The chief clay mineral is chlorite, followed by illite + smectite; there is little to no kaolinite. The total organic carbon content of the bed sediments remains relatively constant with distance for the main stem (generally 1 to 2 wt%, with one exception), but fluctuates for the tributaries (1 to 6 wt%). The mineralogies of the suspended sediments and sediment flow data were used to calculate the amount of mineral dissolution during transport between Eagle and Pilot Station, a distance of over 2000 km. We estimate that approximately 3 wt% of the quartz, 15 wt% of the feldspar (1 wt% of the alkali and 25 wt% of the plagioclase), and 26 wt% of the carbonates (31 wt% of the calcite and 15 wt% of the dolomite) carried by the river dissolve in this reach. The mineralogies of the suspended sediments change with the season. For example, during the summer of 2002 the quartz content varied by 20 wt%, with a minimum in mid-summer. The calcite content varied by a similar amount, and had a maximum corresponding to the quartz minimum. These modes are related to the relative amount of sediment flowing from the White River system, which is relatively poor in quartz, but rich in carbonate minerals. Suspended total clay minerals varied by as much as 25 wt%, with maxima in mid July, and suspended feldspar varied up to 10 wt%. Suspended sediment data from the summers of 2001 and 2003 support the 2002 trends. A calculation technique was developed to determine theproportion of various sediment sources in a mixed sediment by unmixing its quantitative mineralogy. Results from this method indicate that at least three sediment sources can be identified quantitatively with good accuracy. With this technique, sediment mineralogies can be used to calculate the relative flux of sediment from different tributaries, thereby identifying sediment provenance.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Eiriksdottir, E. S.</author><author>Louvat, P.</author><author>Gislason, S. R.</author><author>Óskarsson, N.</author><author>Hardardóttir, J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Temporal variation of chemical and mechanical weathering in NE Iceland: Evaluation of a steady-state model of erosion</title><secondary-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>78-88</pages><volume>272</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>basalt weathering</keyword><keyword>chemical weathering</keyword><keyword>erosion rates</keyword><keyword>mechanical denudation rate</keyword><keyword>river suspended sediments</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2008</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.epsl.2008.04.005</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Eriksdottir et al. 2008, NE Iceland river SPM chemistry model.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study critically assesses the temporal sensitivity of the steady-state model of erosion that has been applied to chemical and mechanical weathering studies of volcanic islands and the continents, using only one sample from each catchment. The model assumes a geochemical mass balance between the initially unweathered rock of a drainage basin and the dissolved and solid loads of the river. Chemical composition of 178 samples of suspended and dissolved inorganic river constituents, collected in 1998-2002, were studied from five basaltic river catchments in NE Iceland. The Hydrological Service in Iceland has monitored the discharge and the total suspended inorganic matter concentration (SIM) of the glacial rivers for ~ four decades, making it possible to compare modelled and measured SIM fluxes. Concentration of SIM and grain size increased with discharge. As proportion of clay size particles in the SIM samples increased, concentrations of insoluble elements increased and of soluble decreased. The highest proportion of altered basaltic glass was in the clay size particles. The concentration ratio of insoluble elements in the SIM was used along with data on chemical composition of unweathered rocks (high-Mg basalts, tholeiites, rhyolites) to calculate the pristine composition of the original catchment rocks. The calculated rhyolite proportions compare nicely with area-weighted average proportions, from geological maps of these catchments. The calculated composition of the unweathered bedrock was used in the steady-state model, together with the chemical composition of the suspended and dissolved constituents of the river. Seasonal changes in dissolved constituent concentrations resulted in too low modelled concentrations of SIMmod at high discharge (and too high SIMmod at low discharge). Samples collected at annual average river dissolved load yielded SIMmod concentrations close to the measured ones. According to the model, the studied rivers had specific mechanical denudation rates of 1.3-3.0 kg/m2/yr whereas the average measured rates were 0.8-3.5 kg/m2/yr which are among the highest on Earth. This study validates the use of a steady-state model of erosion to estimate mechanical weathering rates at the scale of a river catchment when the collected riverine dissolved load represents the average chemical composition over a mean hydrological year. © 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Enguix González, A.</author><author>Ternero Rodríguez, M.</author><author>Jiménez Sá, J. C.</author><author>Fernández Espinosa, A. J.</author><author>Barragán De La Rosa, F. J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Assessment of metals in sediments in a tributary of Guadalquivir River (Spain). Heavy metal partitioning and relation between the water and sediment system</title><secondary-title>Water, Air, and Soil Pollution</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water, Air, and Soil Pollution</full-title></periodical><pages>11-29</pages><volume>121</volume><issue>1-4</issue><keywords><keyword>Analysis of river sediments</keyword><keyword>Cluster analysis</keyword><keyword>Correlation analysis</keyword><keyword>Factor analysis</keyword><keyword>Guadaira River</keyword><keyword>Metal partitioning</keyword><keyword>Water-sediment interaction</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2000</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1023/a:1005203012514</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://EnguixGonzález et al. 2000, Guadalquivir River, Spain, sediment characteristics.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A physical-chemical characterisation of the sediments of the Guadaira River in Southwest Spain has been carried out, determining twenty-three parameters per sample. Non-treated urban sewage and industrial wastewaters from olive oil and table olives affect this river. The factor analysis of the data shows high organic matter contents with metallic pollution. Consequently, points downstream stand out because of very high organic and metallic pollution (Zn, Pb, Cr, Cu and Cd, in order of abundance, showing concentrations in sediments ranging from 50-7500 times those of waters). Heavy metals partitioning studies can be a good approach to show the real activity of these metals in the aquatic environment. We applied Tessier's analytical sequential extraction scheme to sediments. Sediments would be in general mildly hazardous because we found low levels of easily interchangeable metals in the first fraction. Nevertheless, that is not the case in the river's last stretch, precisely where sediments are most abundant, the heavy metal levels largest and dredgings are made periodically. Here, their disposal is of concern; since the actual use of these sediments as organic amendment for agricultural soils is unacceptable. Interaction between waters and sediments in the riverbed by means of correlation, factor and cluster analysis on waters and sediments data, was investigated. With this approach we concluded that in the final stretch there is a problem of contamination of both, sediments and waters. However, in the middle course only sediments are actually polluted. This corresponds to the previous research, when the situation of waters in this zone was even worse.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Filgueiras, A. V.</author><author>Lavilla, I.</author><author>Bendicho, C.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Evaluation of distribution, mobility and binding behaviour of heavy metals in surficial sediments of Louro River (Galicia, Spain) using chemometric analysis: A case study</title><secondary-title>Science of the Total Environment</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science of the Total Environment</full-title></periodical><pages>115-129</pages><volume>330</volume><issue>1-3</issue><keywords><keyword>Heavy metals</keyword><keyword>Pollution sources</keyword><keyword>Principal component analysis</keyword><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>Total and extractable contents</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.scitotenv.2004.03.038</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Filgueiras et al. 2004, Luoro River surface bed sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Contents of total and extractable heavy metals, carbonates, MnO and Fe 2O3, organic matter, and matrix components such as SiO2, Al2O3, CaO, Na2O, MgO, TiO2, K2O and P2O5 are used along with principal component analysis (PCA) for studying distribution, mobility and binding behaviour of Cd, Cr, Cu, Ni and Pb in the Louro River (Galicia, Spain). Eleven surficial sediment samples were taken along the beds of the river course. Total metal concentrations were obtained after microwave-assisted digestion whilst extractable metal contents were obtained following a three-stage sequential extraction scheme (i.e. soluble, reducible and oxidisable fractions). Loading plots of heavy metals bound to carbonates, Fe-Mn oxides, organic matter and aluminosilicates allowed determination of binding behaviour. Correlations found indicate that Pb and Cu are mainly discharged from urban wastes, whereas Cr and Ni are from electroplating and galvanizing industries. The occurrence of diffuse pollution sources along the river can account for the binding behaviour of Cd. Metal mobility decreased in the order: Cd&gt;Pb&gt;Cu&gt;Ni&gt;Cr. Despite total contents indicating moderate-to-high heavy metal pollution in this river, metals are mostly distributed in the residual fraction, hence showing a low risk of mobility. © 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gaiero, Diego M.</author><author>Brunet, Frederic</author><author>Probst, Jean Luc</author><author>Depetris, Pedro J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>A uniform isotopic and chemical signature of dust exported from Patagonia: Rock sources and occurrence in southern environments</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>107-120</pages><volume>238</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Dust source</keyword><keyword>Major and trace elements</keyword><keyword>Patagonia</keyword><keyword>Radiogenic isotopes</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2007</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2006.11.003</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gaiero et al. 2007, Patagonia materials chemical and isotopic signature.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Patagonia is considered to be the most important source of dust from South America that is deposited in surrounding areas, and we present here a systematic Sr and Nd isotopic study of sediment currently being exported. Eolian and suspended riverine sediments from Patagonia have a homogeneous chemical and isotopic composition that results from the mixing of by-products from explosive Andean volcanism, derived from the extensive Jurassic silicic Province of Chon Aike and pyroclastic materials from the basic to intermediate southern Andean Quaternary arc, which are easily denudated and dispersed. The main Andean uplift and the glaciations that began in the Late Tertiary account for the extensive distribution of these sediments in the extra-Andean region. The present geochemical signature of Patagonian sediments was produced during the Pleistocene, along with the onset of the southern Andean explosive arc volcanism. Previously published compositions of sediments from other southern South American source regions, assumed to be representative of Patagonia, are distinct from our data. Considering the alleged importance of Patagonia as a dust source for different depositional environments in southern latitudes, it is surprising to verify that the chemical and isotopic signatures of Patagonian-sourced sediments are different from those of sediments from the Southern Ocean, the Pampean Region or the Antarctic ice. Sediments from these areas have a crustal-like geochemical signature reflecting a mixed origin with sediment from other southern South American sources, whereas Patagonian sediments likely represent the basic to intermediate end-member composition. © 2006 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gaillardet, J.</author><author>Dupré, B.</author><author>Allègre, C. J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of large river suspended sediments: Silicate weathering or recycling tracer?</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>4037-4051</pages><volume>63</volume><issue>23-24</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/s0016-7037(99)00307-5</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gaillardet et al. 1999, Large River SPM geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study focuses on the major and trace element composition of suspended sediments transported by the world's largest rivers. Its main purpose is to answer the following question: is the degree of weathering of modern river-borne particles consistent with the estimated river dissolved loads derived from silicate weathering? In agreement with the well known mobility of elements during weathering of continental rocks, we confirm that river sediments are systematically depleted in Na, K, Ba with respect to the Upper Continental Crust. For each of these mobile elements, a systematics of weathering indexes of river-borne solids is attempted. A global consistency is found between all these indexes. Important variations in weathering intensities exist. A clear dependence of weathering intensities with climate is observed for the rivers draining mostly lowlands. However, no global correlation exists between weathering intensities and climatic or relief parameters because the trend observed for lowlands is obscured by rivers draining orogenic zones. An inverse correlation between weathering intensities and suspended sediment concentrations is observed showing that the regions having the highest rates of physical denudation produce the least weathered sediments. Finally, chemical and physical weathering are compared through the use of a simple steady state model. We show that the weathering intensities of large river suspended sediments can only be reconciled with the (silicate-derived) dissolved load of rivers, by admitting that most of the continental rocks submitted to weathering in large river basins have already suffered previous weathering cycles. A simple graphical method is proposed for calculating the proportion of sedimentary recycling in large river basins. Finally, even if orogenic zones produce weakly weathered sediments, we emphasize the fact that silicate chemical weathering rates (and hence CO2 consumption rates by silicate weathering) are greatly enhanced in mountains simply because the sediment yields in orogenic drainage basins are higher. Hence, the parameters that control chemical weathering rates would be those that control physical denudation rates.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gaillardet, Jérôme</author><author>Millot, Romain</author><author>Dupré, Bernard</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Chemical denudation rates of the western Canadian orogenic belt: The Stikine terrane</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>257-279</pages><volume>201</volume><issue>3-4</issue><keywords><keyword>Ca/Na ratio</keyword><keyword>Canadian Cordillera</keyword><keyword>Rivers</keyword><keyword>Silicate weathering</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2003.07.001</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gaillardet et al. 2003,Skeena basin, West Canada, SPM + Dissolved.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We report in this paper major element and Sr isotopic ratio analyses for 19 rivers draining the Stikine Province in the Western Canadian Cordillera. Dissolved solutes, suspended sediments and river sands were analyzed. The aim of the paper is to calculate chemical denudation rates for this uplifted accretionary prism, mainly dominated by volcanics and volcanic-derived sedimentary rocks. The major chemical features of the Stikine rivers are their dilute character and the excess of Ca, Mg and Sr in the dissolved load with regards to Na. Molar Ca/Na ratios from 2 to 14, mean value of 5.4, are observed although the region is dominated by silicate rocks. Suspended sediments show Ca/Na ratios close to 0.4. Isotopically, most of the rivers investigated display lower Sr isotopic ratios in the dissolved load compared to the suspended load, which is very unusual. To account for the excess of cations, three different hypotheses are tested by an inversion method allowing us to determine the origin of each major solute. The first scenario assumes that the excess of Ca and Mg is due to the dissolution of unradiogenic carbonates. The second scenario supposes that the excess of base cations is derived from the preferential dissolution of Ca- and Mg-rich minerals, such as amphiboles. In the third scenario, all solutes are assumed to derived from silicate weathering. The cationic weathering rates of silicates, although imprecise, are in the order of 2-5 tons/km2/year for the two first hypotheses. If all solutes are taken into account, denudation rates are between 9 and 15 tons/km2/year. On a global scale, these numbers are among the lowest found for rivers draining basaltic rocks. They are however found to be consistent with the global law for chemical weathering rates established for basaltic rocks showing that chemical denudation rate are linearly correlated to runoff and depend on temperature according to an Arrhenius law. The rivers draining the complex assemblage of volcanic and volcanic-derived rocks in the subduction/ collision geological context of the Stikine Province thus respond similarly to the other volcanic provinces of the world. This does not seem to be true for associated CO2 consumption rates. The abundance of sulfate ions in the dissolved load, possibly derived from oxidative weathering of sulfides, may indeed provide a non-negligible part of the protons necessary for chemical weathering. Within Canada, the Stikine geologic province is one whose silicates weather at a high rate. The order of chemical weatherabilty of Canadian geological province from the lowest to the highest is established as follows: granites &lt; shales of the rockies &lt; volcanics of the Western Cordillera &lt; shales of the interior platform &lt; carbonates. © 2003 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Galy, Albert</author><author>France-Lanord, Christian</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Higher erosion rates in the Himalaya: Geochemical constraints on riverine fluxes</title><secondary-title>Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>23-26</pages><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords><keyword>Geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Isotope</keyword><keyword>Mass balance</keyword><keyword>Neodymium</keyword><keyword>Sediment</keyword><keyword>Silicon</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2001</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1130/0091-7613(2001)029&lt;0023:HERITH&gt;2.0.CO;2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Galy &amp; France-Lanord 2001, Ganga-Brahmaputra SPM &amp; bed load geochemical flux.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The modern erosion rate of continental-scale mountains is difficult to estimate and is usually based on measurement of the suspended load flux of rivers combined with assumptions about river bedload transport and sedimentation in flood plains. These two parameters are very difficult to measure directly in continental-scale basins. In this paper we examine the chemical composition of the suspended load, bedload, and dissolved load of the Ganga and Brahmaputra Rivers and compare them with the average composition of Himalayan source rocks. A mass-balance equation of erosion fluxes shows that a Si-rich component is needed in addition to suspended and dissolved load fluxes to account for the composition of the source rock. It corresponds to bedload sediment and flood-plain deposits, which are enriched in quartz by mineral sorting during transport. The combined budget of Si, Al, and Fe in the river system allows us to estimate this Si-rich flux. By this method, the total Himalayan erosion is estimated to be twice the measured flux of suspended load. The comparison between the Brahmaputra and the Ganga shows that the eastern Himalaya has a higher erosion rate (2.9 mm/yr) than the western Himalaya (2.1 mm/yr). This is likely the result of the higher runoff in the Brahmaputra basin. The intensity of the monsoon acts as a first-order control of the erosion rate in the range.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Al-Juboury, Ali Ismail</author><author>Zoleikhaei, Yousef</author><author>Vermeesch, Pieter</author><author>Jotheri, Jaafar</author><author>Akkoca, Dicle Bal</author><author>Obaid, Ahmed Kadhim</author><author>Allen, Mark B.</author><author>Andó, Sergio</author><author>Limonta, Mara</author><author>Padoan, Marta</author><author>Resentini, Alberto</author><author>Rittner, Martin</author><author>Vezzoli, Giovanni</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The Euphrates-Tigris-Karun river system: Provenance, recycling and dispersal of quartz-poor foreland-basin sediments in arid climate</title><secondary-title>Earth-Science Reviews</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth-Science Reviews</full-title></periodical><pages>107-128</pages><volume>162</volume><keywords><keyword>Anatolia-Zagros orogen</keyword><keyword>Heavy minerals</keyword><keyword>Long-distance sediment transport</keyword><keyword>Sedimentary petrology</keyword><keyword>Undissected collision orogen provenance</keyword><keyword>U–Pb zircon geochronology</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.earscirev.2016.09.009</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al. 2016, Euphrates&amp;Tigris review.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2016.09.009</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>We present a detailed sediment-provenance study on the modern Euphrates-Tigris-Karun fluvial system and Mesopotamian foreland basin, one of the cradles of humanity. Our rich petrographic and heavy-mineral dataset, integrated by sand geochemistry and U–Pb age spectra of detrital zircons, highlights the several peculiarities of this large source-to-sink sediment-routing system and widens the spectrum of compositions generally assumed as paradigmatic for orogenic settings. Comparison of classical static versus upgraded dynamic petrologic models enhances the power of provenance analysis, and allows us to derive a more refined conceptual model of reference and to verify the limitations of the approach. Sand derived from the Anatolia-Zagros orogen contains abundant lithic grains eroded from carbonates, cherts, mudrocks, arc volcanics, obducted ophiolites and ophiolitic mélanges representing the exposed shallow structural level of the orogen, with relative scarcity of quartz, K-feldspar and mica. This quartz-poor petrographic signature, characterizing the undissected composite tectonic domain of the entire Anatolia-Iranian plateau, is markedly distinct from that of sand shed by more elevated and faster-eroding collision orogens such as the Himalaya. Arid climate in the region allows preservation of chemically unstable grains including carbonate rock fragments and locally even gypsum, and reduces transport capacity of fluvial systems, which dump most of their load in Mesopotamian marshlands upstream of the Arabian/Persian Gulf allochemical carbonate factory. Quartz-poor sediment from the Anatolia-Zagros orogen mixes with quartz-rich recycled sands from Arabia along the western side of the foreland basin, and is traced all along the Gulf shores as far as the Rub' al-Khali sand sea up to 4000 km from Euphrates headwaters.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Andó, Sergio</author><author>France-Lanord, Christian</author><author>Censi, Paolo</author><author>Vignola, Pietro</author><author>Galy, Valier</author><author>Lupker, Maarten</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mineralogical and chemical variability of fluvial sediments 2. Suspended-load silt (Ganga-Brahmaputra, Bangladesh)</title><secondary-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>107-120</pages><volume>302</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>REE geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Raman spectroscopy</keyword><keyword>Settling equivalence</keyword><keyword>Silt mineralogy</keyword><keyword>Suspension sorting</keyword><keyword>Weathering indices</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2011</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.epsl.2010.11.043</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://garzanti2011_Brahmaputra, Bangladesh, mineralogy and chemisrty SPM raman.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2010.11.043</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Sediments carried in suspension represent a fundamental part of fluvial transport. Nonetheless, largely because of technical problems, they have been hitherto widely neglected in provenance studies. In order to determine with maximum possible precision the mineralogy of suspended load collected in vertical profiles from water surface to channel bottom of Rivers Ganga and Brahmaputra, we combined Raman spectroscopy with traditional heavy-mineral and X-ray diffraction analyses, carried out separately on low-density and dense fractions of all significant size classes in each sample (multiple-window approach). Suspended load resulted to be a ternary mixture of dominant silt enriched in phyllosilicates, subordinate clay largely derived from weathered floodplains, and sand mainly produced by physical erosion and mechanical grinding during transport in Himalayan streams. Sediment concentration and grain size increase steadily with water depth. Whereas absolute concentration of clay associated with Fe-oxyhydroxides and organic matter is almost depth-invariant, regular mineralogical and consequently chemical changes from shallow to deep load result from marked increase of faster-settling, coarser, denser, or more spherical grains toward the bed. Such steady intersample compositional variability can be modeled as a mixture of clay, silt and sand modes with distinct mineralogical and chemical composition. With classical formulas describing sediment transport by turbulent diffusion, absolute and relative concentrations can be predicted at any depth for each textural mode and each detrital component. Based on assumptions on average chemistry of detrital minerals and empirical formulas to calculate their settling velocities, the suspension-sorting model successfully reproduces mineralogy and chemistry of suspended load at different depths. Principal outputs include assessment of contributions by each detrital mineral to the chemical budget, and calibration of dense minerals too rare to be precisely estimated by optical or Raman analysis but crucial in both detrital-geochronology and settling-equivalence studies. Hydrodynamic conditions during monsoonal discharge could also be evaluated. Understanding compositional variability of suspended load is a fundamental pre-requisite to correctly interpret mineralogical and geochemical data in provenance analysis of modern and ancient sedimentary deposits, to accurately assess weathering processes, sediment fluxes and erosion patterns, and to unambiguously evaluate the effects of anthropogenic modifications on the natural environment. © 2010 Elsevier B.V.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Andò, Sergio</author><author>Padoan, Marta</author><author>Vezzoli, Giovanni</author><author>El Kammar, Ahmed</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The modern Nile sediment system: Processes and products</title><secondary-title>Quaternary Science Reviews</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Quaternary Science Reviews</full-title></periodical><pages>9-56</pages><volume>130</volume><keywords><keyword>Anorogenic Volcanic provenance</keyword><keyword>Continental block provenance</keyword><keyword>Erosion rates and sediment budgets</keyword><keyword>Geochemistry and chemical weathering</keyword><keyword>Heavy minerals and hydraulic sorting</keyword><keyword>Long-distance littoral transport</keyword><keyword>Sediment mixing and recycling</keyword><keyword>Sedimentary petrology and provenance models</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2015</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.quascirev.2015.07.011</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al. 2015, Modern Nile River sediment system.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>We trace compositional changes of Nile sediments for 7400 km, from their sources in equatorial rift highlands of Burundi and Rwanda to their sink in the Mediterranean Sea. All chemical and physical controls on sediment petrography, mineralogy and geochemistry, including weathering, grain-size, hydraulic sorting, mechanical breakdown, anthropic impact, mixing and recycling are investigated in detail. The Nile course is controlled along its entire length by the East African-Red Sea Rift. In this anorogenic setting, detritus is derived in various proportions from volcanic fields associated with tectonic extension (Anorogenic Volcanic provenance) and from igneous, metamorphic and sedimentary rocks uplifted on the rift shoulders or exposed on the craton (Continental Block provenance). The entire spectrum of such detrital signatures is displayed in the Nile catchment. Volcaniclastic Atbara sand is generated by focused erosion of the Ethiopian basaltic plateau in semiarid climate, whereas quartzose White Nile sand reflects low erosion rates, extensive weathering and sediment trapping in lakes and swamps at equatorial to subequatorial latitudes. In the main Nile, as in its main tributary the Blue Nile, suspended load is volcaniclastic, whereas feldspatho-quartzose bedload is derived largely from basement sources, with fine to medium-grained eolian sand added along the lower course. Mixing of detrital populations with different provenance and grain size is reflected in diverse violations of settling-equivalence relationships in fluvial and deltaic sediments. Sediment delivery from Sudan has been cut off after closure of the Aswan High Dam and accelerated erosion of deltaic cusps is leading to local formation of placer lags dominated by ultradense Fe-Ti-Cr oxides, but mineralogical changes caused by man's radical modification of fluvial regimes have been minor so far. In beaches of Sinai, Gaza and Israel, the Nile volcaniclastic trace gets progressively diluted by quartzose sand recycled from eolian coastal deposits and carbonaticlastic detritus eroded from the Levant rift shoulder. Studying the compositional variability of modern sediments in big-river systems allows us to appreciate the richness of natural processes occurring in the vast drainage basin, and provides us with a key to understand the information stored in sedimentary archives and to reconstruct the evolution of the Earth's surface from the recent to the less recent past.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Liang, Wendong</author><author>Andò, Sergio</author><author>Clift, Peter D.</author><author>Resentini, Alberto</author><author>Vermeesch, Pieter</author><author>Vezzoli, Giovanni</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Provenance of Thal Desert sand: Focused erosion in the western Himalayan syntaxis and foreland-basin deposition driven by latest Quaternary climate change</title><secondary-title>Earth-Science Reviews</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth-Science Reviews</full-title></periodical><volume>207</volume><issue>June</issue><keywords><keyword>Detrital-zircon geochronology</keyword><keyword>Focused erosion</keyword><keyword>Himalaya-Karakorum</keyword><keyword>Indus River, Delta, and Fan</keyword><keyword>Kohistan arc</keyword><keyword>Sand petrography and geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Variability of εNd values</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.earscirev.2020.103220</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al. 2020, Indus, Thal desert provenance.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>As a latest Pleistocene repository of Indus River sand at the entry point to the Himalayan foreland basin, the Thal dune field in northern Pakistan stores crucial information that can be used to reconstruct the erosional evolution of the Himalayan-Karakorum orogen and the changes in the foreland-basin landscape that took place between the Last Glacial Maximum and the early Holocene. This comprehensive provenance study of Thal Desert sand integrates previously existing petrographic, heavy-mineral, mineral-chemical, isotopic, and geochronological databases with original bulk-sediment geochemistry, zircon-age, and Nd-isotope data. Dune sand is low in quartz and rich in feldspars, volcanic, metavolcanic and metabasite grains, contains a very rich transparent heavy-mineral suite including hypersthene and common zircon grains dated as Late Cretaceous to early Paleogene, and is characterized by high Mg, Sc, V, Co, Ni, Cu concentrations and by εNd values as high as −3.5. Together, these data indicate that ~40% of Thal dune sand was supplied by erosion of the Kohistan arc, a proportion that far exceeds the one assessed for modern Upper Indus sand. Greater detrital supply from the Kohistan arc indicates notably different conditions of sediment generation, during a period in which the sediment-transport capacity of the Upper Indus in the dry lowlands was reduced and volumes of sand were extensively reworked by wind and accumulated in dune fields across the foreland basin. In the early Holocene, the renewed strength of the South Asian monsoon and consequently markedly increased water and sediment discharge led to incision of the Thal and Thar dune fields by the Indus River and its Punjab tributaries draining the Himalayan front directly hit by heavy monsoonal rains.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Padoan, Marta</author><author>Setti, Massimo</author><author>López-Galindo, Alberto</author><author>Villa, Igor M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Provenance versus weathering control on the composition of tropical river mud (southern Africa)</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>61-74</pages><volume>366</volume><keywords><keyword>Chemical weathering indices</keyword><keyword>Clay minerals</keyword><keyword>Model mantle derivation ages</keyword><keyword>Recycling</keyword><keyword>Sr and Nd isotopic ratios</keyword><keyword>Zambezi, Limpopo and Okavango Rivers</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2014</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2013.12.016</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al.  2014, Southern African River SPM Geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study presents an integrated mineralogical-geochemical database on fine-grained sediments transported by all major rivers of southern Africa, including the Zambezi, Okavango, Limpopo, Olifants, Orange and Kunene. Clay mineralogy, bulk geochemistry, Sr and Nd isotopic signatures of river mud, considered a proxy of suspended load, are used to investigate the influence of source-rock lithology and weathering intensity on the composition of clay and silt produced in subequatorial to subtropical latitudes. Depletion in mobile alkali and alkaline-earth metals, minor in arid Namibia, is strong in the Okavango, Kwando and Upper Zambezi catchments, where recycling is also extensive. Element removal is most significant for Na, and to a lesser extent for Sr. Depletion in K, Ca and other elements, negligible in Namibia, is moderate elsewhere. The most widespread clay minerals are smectite, dominant in muds derived from Karoo or Etendeka flood basalts, or illite and chlorite, dominant in muds derived from metasedimentary rocks of the Damara Orogen or Zimbabwe Craton. Kaolinite represents 30-40% of clay minerals only in Okavango and Upper Zambezi sediments sourced in humid subequatorial Angola and Zambia. After subtracting the effects of recycling and of local accumulation of authigenic carbonates in soils, the regional distribution of clay minerals and chemical indices consistently reflect weathering intensity primarily controlled by climate. Bulk geochemistry identifies most clearly volcaniclastic sediments and mafic sources in general, but cannot discriminate the other sources of detritus in detail. Instead, Sr and Nd isotopic fingerprints are insensitive to weathering, and thus mirror faithfully the tectonic structure of the southern African continent. Isotopic tools thus represent a much firmer basis than bulk geochemistry or clay mineralogy in the provenance study of mudrocks. © 2013 Elsevier B.V.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Resentini, Alberto</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Provenance control on chemical indices of weathering (Taiwan river sands)</title><secondary-title>Sedimentary Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Sedimentary Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>81-95</pages><volume>336</volume><keywords><keyword>CIA PIA, CIW, CIX, WIP indices</keyword><keyword>Climate and paleoclimate</keyword><keyword>Grain size and hydraulic sorting</keyword><keyword>Provenance and heavy minerals</keyword><keyword>Sedimentary geochemistry</keyword><keyword>αAl values</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.sedgeo.2015.06.013</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al. 2016c, Taiwan river sand provenance.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sedgeo.2015.06.013</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Geochemical parameters obtained from the analysis of sediments and sedimentary rocks are widely used to infer weathering and paleo-weathering conditions in source areas. Chemical indices of weathering, however, may not reflect weathering only, or even principally. The concentration of chemical elements in terrigenous sediments is constrained by the original mineralogy of source rocks, and is thus provenance-dependent. Moreover, the mineralogy and consequently the geochemistry of sediments may undergo substantial modifications by diverse physical processes during transport and deposition, including recycling and hydraulic sorting by size, density or shape, and/or by chemical dissolution and precipitation during diagenesis.Around the island of Taiwan, temperature and rainfall are consistently high and relatively homogeneous, and no significant correlation is observed between geochemical and climatic parameters. Physical erosion, fostered by landslides induced by frequent earthquakes and typhoons, prevails because of high relief and extreme rates of tectonic uplift. In such a dynamic orogenic setting, all chemical indices of weathering are controlled principally by the geology of source terranes. Sedimentaclastic and metasedimentaclastic sands carried by western Taiwan rivers draining the pro-wedge display the strongest depletion in Na, Ca, Mg and Sr relative to average upper continental crust, and no depletion or even enrichment in K, Rb and Ba. Low WIP indices reflect erosion of phyllosilicate-dominated rocks in the Slate Belt and extensive recycling of clastic rocks exposed in the Western Foothills. Instead, metamorphiclastic sands carried by eastern Taiwan rivers draining the retro-wedge show no depletion or even enrichment in Mg and Ca, and low CIA and PIA, reflecting contributions from the Tailuko Belt and Coastal Range. Volcaniclastic sands have the same CIA values of their andesitic source rocks (47 ± 1 versus 47 ± 7), indicating that weathering is subordinate both along the eastern side of the island and at its northern edge where annual rainfall is double.Full caution is required when chemical weathering indices are used to extract climatic and paleoclimatic information from the sedimentary archive, especially in the case of diagenized sandstones where commonly massive precipitation of authigenic carbonate is very difficult to accurately correct for, especially in the absence of detailed petrographic and mineralogical data.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Vezzoli, Giovanni</author><author>Andò, Sergio</author><author>Paparella, Paolo</author><author>Clift, Peter D.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Petrology of Indus River sands: A key to interpret erosion history of the Western Himalayan Syntaxis</title><secondary-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>287-302</pages><volume>229</volume><issue>3-4</issue><keywords><keyword>Bulk petrography</keyword><keyword>Collision orogens</keyword><keyword>Heavy minerals</keyword><keyword>Himalaya</keyword><keyword>Karakorum</keyword><keyword>Modern sands</keyword><keyword>Nanga Parbat</keyword><keyword>Sediment budgets</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2005</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.epsl.2004.11.008</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al. 2005 Indus river sand petrology.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The Indus River has been progressively transformed in the last decades into a tightly regulated system of dams and channels, to produce food and energy for the rapidly growing population of Pakistan. Nevertheless, Indus River sands as far as the delta largely retain their distinct feldspar- and amphibole-rich composition, which is unique with respect to all other major rivers draining the Alpine-Himalayan belt except for the Brahmaputra. Both the Indus and Brahmaputra Rivers flow for half of their course along the India-Asia suture zone, and receive major contributions from both Asian active-margin batholiths and upper-amphibolite-facies domes rapidly exhumed at the Western and Eastern Himalayan syntaxes. Composition of Indus sands changes repeated ly and markedly in Ladakh and Baltistan, indicating overwhelming sediment flux from each successive tributary as the syntaxis is approached. Provenance estimates based on our integrated petrographic-mineralogical data set indicate that active-margin units (Karakorum and Transhimalayan arcs) provide ∼81% of the 250±50 106 t of sediments reaching the Tarbela reservoir each year. Partitioning of such flux among tributaries and among source units allows us to tentatively assess sediment yields from major subcatchments. Extreme yields and erosion rates are calculated for both the Karakorum Belt (up to 12,500±4700 t/km2 year and 4.5 ± 1.7 mm/year for the Braldu catchment) and Nanga Parbat Massif (8100±3500 t/km2 year and 3.0±1.3 mm/year). These values approach denudation rates currently estimated for South Karakorum and Nanga Parbat crustal-scale antiforms, and highlight the major influence that rapid tectonic uplift and focused glacial and fluvial erosion of young metamorphic massifs around the Western Himalayan Syntaxis have on sediment budgets of the Indus system. Detailed information on bulk petrography and heavy minera ls of modern Indus sands not only represents an effective independent method to constrain denudation rates obtained from temperature-time histories of exposed bedrock, but also provides an actualistic reference for collision-orogen provenance, and gives us a key to interpreting provenance and paleodrainage changes recorded by clastic wedges deposited in the Himalayan foreland basin and Arabian Sea during the Cenozoic. © 2004 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Wang, Jiang Gang</author><author>Vezzoli, Giovanni</author><author>Limonta, Mara</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Tracing provenance and sediment fluxes in the Irrawaddy River basin (Myanmar)</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>73-90</pages><volume>440</volume><keywords><keyword>Bulk-sediment geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Detrital zircon U-Pb geochronology</keyword><keyword>Heavy minerals</keyword><keyword>Sand petrology</keyword><keyword>Stream-profile analysis</keyword><keyword>Tectonic geomorphology</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2016.06.010</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Garzanti et al. 2016, Irrawady River sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2016.06.010</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>This study illustrates the petrographic, heavy-mineral, geochemical and geochronological signatures of sand transported by various branches of the Irrawaddy (Ayeyarwadi) River, one of the first in the world for sediment flux. Intrasample and intersample compositional variability, weathering and hydraulic-sorting controls are also discussed. Feldspatho-quartzose sand in Irrawaddy headwaters is largely derived first-cycle from mid-crustal metamorphic and plutonic rocks of the Mogok Belt and Lohit complex, whereas feldspatho-litho-quartzose Chindwin sand is largely recycled from supracrustal, sedimentary and very low-grade metasedimentary units. Additional mafic to ultramafic detritus is derived from ophiolites and blueschists exposed from the Indo-Burman Ranges to the Jade Mines and Myitkyina belts, linked northward to the Yarlung-Tsangpo suture of the Himalaya. Volcanic detritus derived from the Popa-Wuntho arc or recycled from forearc-basin strata also occurs. Decreasing concentration of most chemical elements along the Irrawaddy reflects progressive addition of detritus recycled from sedimentary rocks, most evident downstream of the Chindwin confluence. REE patterns with LREE enrichment and negative Eu anomaly reflect the occurrence of allanite, largely derived from granitoid rocks in the Mali catchment. Chemical indices indicate moderate weathering in the monsoon-dominated climate of Myanmar. Young U-Pb ages (15–170 Ma) represent 85% of detrital zircons in Irrawaddy headwater branches, reflecting long-lasting subduction-related magmatism along a ring of fire connecting with the southern and central Lhasa batholiths in Tibet and polyphase metamorphism in the Mogok belt. Chindwin sand contains larger amounts of finer-grained, recycled pre-Mesozoic zircons, also yielding early Mesoproterozoic to Archean ages. Such different petrographic, heavy-mineral, geochemical and geochronological fingerprints characterizing sand in different river branches allowed us to calculate bulk-sediment and zircon-provenance budgets that converge to indicate equivalent sand supply from the Nmai and Mali Rivers to the upper Irrawaddy, and from the Chindwin and upper Irrawaddy to the lower Irrawaddy. This implies that despite of higher erosion potential indicated by stream-profile analysis in high-relief Irrawaddy headwaters, sediment yields and erosion rates are detectably higher in the Chindwin catchment, which is mainly ascribed to higher erodibility of widely exposed siliciclastic rocks. Quantifying sediment provenance and defining erosion patterns based on an integrated compositional database in a big-river system such as the mighty Irrawaddy allows us to expand our understanding of sediment-generation processes with the ultimate goal to increase our capacity to read into the stratigraphic record.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gordeev, V. V.</author><author>Rachold, V.</author><author>Vlasova, I. E.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemical behaviour of major and trace elements in suspended particulate material of the Irtysh river, the main tributary of the Ob river, Siberia</title><secondary-title>Applied Geochemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Applied Geochemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>593-610</pages><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.apgeochem.2003.08.004</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gordeev et al. 2004, Ob and Irtysh river SPM geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>In July 2001, samples of surface suspended particulate material (SPM) of the Irtysh river in its middle and lower reaches (from Omsk City to the confluence with the Ob river) and its main tributaries were collected (18 stations along 1834 km). The SPM samples were analyzed for major and trace element composition. The results show that the geochemistry of Irtysh river SPM is related to landscape and geochemical peculiarities of the river basin on one hand and to industrial activities within the drainage area on the other hand. In the upper basin polymetallic and cinnabar deposits and phosphorite deposits with high As content are widespread. The open-cut mining and developed oil-refining, power plants and other industries lead to the contamination of the environment by heavy metals and other contaminants. The territory of the West Siberian lowland, especially the Ob-Irtysh interfluve, is characterized by the occurrence of swamps and peat-bogs. Tributaries of the Irtysh river originating in this region, have a brown color and the chemical composition of the SPM is specific for stagnant water. In the first 500-700 km downstream from Omsk City the Irtysh river has the typical Al-Si-rich suspended matter composition. After the inflow of the tributaries with brown water the SPM composition is significantly changed: an increase of POC, Fe, P, Ca, Sr, Ba and As concentrations and a strong decrease of the lithogenic elements Al, Mg, K, Na, Ti, Zr can be observed. The data show that Fe-organic components (Fe-humic amorphous compounds, which contribute ca. 75-85% to the total Fe) play a very important role in SPM of the tributaries with brown water and in the Irtysh river in its lower reaches. Among the trace metals significant enrichments relative to the average for global river SPM could only be observed for As and Cd (coefficient of enrichment up to 16 for As and 3-3.5 for Cd). It can be shown that the enrichment of As in the SPM is related to natural processes, i.e. the weathering of phosphate containing deposits with high As concentrations in the upper Irtysh basin and the high As-P affinity in the swamp peaty soil. Dissolved P and As are absorbed by amorphous organic C/Fe oxyhydroxide components which act as carriers during the transport to the main stream of the Irtysh river. The role of anthropogenic factors is probably insignificant for As. In contrast, the enrichment of Cd is mainly related to anthropogenic input. The threefold enrichment of Cd in the SPM just below Omsk City and its continuous decrease down to background level at a distance of 500-700 km downstream points quite definitely to the municipal and industrial sewage of Omsk City as the main source of Cd in the SPM of the Irtysh river. © 2003 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gordeev, V. V.</author><author>Shevchenko, V. P.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Forms of some metals in the suspended sediments of the Northern Dvina River and their seasonal variations</title><secondary-title>Oceanology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Oceanology</full-title></periodical><pages>261-270</pages><volume>52</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2012</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1134/S0001437012010092</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://gordeev2012_S Dvina River, Russia, SPM metals.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The results of the analysis of samples of the Northern Dvina River's suspended particulate matter obtained by the sedimentation method from large water volumes in the periods of the spring high water and summer low water are presented. By the method of sequential leaching using different reagents, four fractions have been separated: the F1 is the sorbed complex and carbonates, the F2 is the amorphous hydroxides of Fe and Mn, the F3 is the form connected with the organic matter, and the F4 is the residual or silicate-detrital (inert) form. The data have shown that all ten elements determined were grouped with respect to the ratio of the distinguished forms: F4 is the predominant form for Al and Fe (73-88% of all the forms; however, the summer sample contains only 38% of this form of iron, and F2 is the predominant form for this period with 46.6%). As to Mn, the F1, F2, and F4 are nearly equally distributed in the spring high water samples, and only the F3 form is less important (5.4%). In the summer sample, the manganese sorbed complex is predominant (53.5%); for Cu, Ni, Cr, and Co, the inert F4 form is predominant (60-70%) in the sample of the spring suspended matter. The summer low water suspended matter has a lower F4 contribution (25-45%); for Zn, Pb, and Cd, the equal distribution of the forms in the spring samples is typical, while the summer suspended matter differs by the F2 form's predominance (53-61% for Zn and Pb). The main conclusion from the acquired data is that the geochemical mobility of all the studied elements, except for cadmium, in the summer low water suspended matter is higher than in the spring suspended matter. The more intensive biogeochemical processes in August, the high level of organic matter, and the higher contribution of phytoplankton lead to the intensification of the metals' geochemical activity in the Northern Dvina suspended matter in the end of the summer compared to the spring high water period when the physical processes are predominant over the biogeochemical ones due to the high speeds of the freshened waters flow. © 2012 Pleiades Publishing, Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Gordeev, Viacheslav V</author><author>Beeskow, Bettina</author><author>Meeresforschung, Polar- U N D</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of the Ob and Yenisey Estuaries : A comparative study</title><secondary-title>Berichte zur Polar- und Meeresforschung</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Berichte zur Polar- und Meeresforschung</full-title></periodical><volume>565</volume><keywords/><dates><year>2007</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Gordeev et al. Ob and Yenisey estuaries SPM and Diss chem.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Grosbois, C.</author><author>Négrel, P.</author><author>Grimaud, D.</author><author>Fouillac, C.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>An overview of dissolved and suspended matter fluxes in the Loire River Basin: Natural and anthropogenic inputs</title><secondary-title>Aquatic Geochemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Aquatic Geochemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>81-105</pages><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Anthropogenic inputs</keyword><keyword>Authigenic calcite</keyword><keyword>Dissolved load</keyword><keyword>Flux calculation</keyword><keyword>Loire River</keyword><keyword>Natural inputs</keyword><keyword>Suspended matter</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2001</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1023/A:1017518831860</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://grosbois2001_Loire River, France, SPM &amp; diss fluxes.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The spatial and temporal distributions of major elements were investigated in the surface waters and in associated suspended matter at two sites of the upper Loire basin (Orleans and Brehemont) between 1995 and 1998. According to geochemical and isotopic patterns, the dissolved load appears to result from a process of mixing rainwater inputs, weathering processes of carbonate and silicate bedrock, and agricultural and urban inputs. Natural inputs influence 60% of water chemical composition at both sites. Annual dissolved fluxes were estimated to be 1300 103 t/y at Orleans and 1620 103 t/y at Brehemont. Major elements are transported mainly in the dissolved fraction. After correcting for atmospheric and anthropogenic inputs, the silicate specific export rate was calculated to be 11 t/y/km2 throughout the basin and the carbonate specific export rate to be from 47 t/y/km2 at Orleans to 23 t/y/km2 at Brehemont. The suspended load appears to result from at least two particle reservoirs: a silicate reservoir and a carbonate reservoir. The silicate reservoir has a detrital origin, mainly during periods of high flow, while the carbonate reservoir has a detrital origin during periods of high flow and an authigenic origin during periods of low flow. Of the total annual flow of suspended matter, this authigenic material represents 16% at Orleans, 25% at Brehemont and 37% in the fluvial part of the estuary. After correcting authigenic inputs, the specific export rate due to mechanical weathering was estimated to be 8 t/y/km2 throughout the Loire basin.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Guinoiseau, Damien</author><author>Bouchez, Julien</author><author>Gélabert, Alexandre</author><author>Louvat, Pascale</author><author>Filizola, Naziano</author><author>Benedetti, Marc F.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The geochemical filter of large river confluences</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>191-203</pages><volume>441</volume><keywords><keyword>Amazonian Basin</keyword><keyword>Elemental flux</keyword><keyword>Geochemical filter</keyword><keyword>River confluence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2016.08.009</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://guinoiseau2016_Confluences RiuNegro Amazon Ca SPM loss.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study reports the behaviour and fate of major and trace elements in solid and solution in the Encontro das Aguas mixing zone in the Amazonian basin. This area results from the confluence of acidic, organic-rich Rio Negro and Andean sediment-rich Rio Solimões. The differences existing between these two water masses are likely to modify the partitioning of elements between solid and solution or to induce losses by physical or chemical removal. To account for lateral and vertical heterogeneities in the river sections, the fluxes of elements in dissolved and solid loads were estimated as accurately as possible using an interpolation technique. A general loss of suspended particulate matter (SPM) of 23% is measured 80 km after the confluence but the various elements and their associated hosted minerals are not affected in a similar way. SiSPM, CaSPM, NaSPM or SrSPM, mostly associated with coarse phases (quartz and Ca-Na feldspars) are preferentially lost. Refractory elements (CoSPM, CrSPM, TiSPM, AlSPM, NiSPM), other alkali (A) and alkali earth (AE) elements (KSPM, MgSPM, BaSPM), FeSPM or organic carbon (OC) are lost to a lesser extent due to their occurrence in finer fractions such as clays (smectite, illite or kaolinite), oxides and particulate organic matter (POM). In solution A-AE and Cudiss, mostly originating from the Rio Solimões behave conservatively. By contrast, refractory elements, coming mostly from the Rio Negro, exhibit important losses (from − 10% for DOC to − 60% for Codiss). Changes in pH and ionic strength during the mixing may induce a sorption of these elements to particles supplied by the Rio Solimões, a clustering and/or a settling of nanokaolinites phases or a sorption of Aldiss, Fediss, Codiss, Mndiss or Zndiss by dissolved organic matter (DOM). The differential elemental settling at a river confluence could thus induce a phase shift between element supply and export out of a watershed. The physical and chemical processes reported here for a river confluence could be applied in other mixing zones such as estuaries or mining exhausts.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Hasholt, Bent</author><author>Hagedorn, Birgit</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Hydrology and Geochemistry of River-borne Material in a High Arctic Drainage System, Zackenberg, Northeast Greenland</title><secondary-title>Arctic, Antarctic, and Alpine Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Arctic, Antarctic, and Alpine Research</full-title></periodical><pages>84-94</pages><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2000</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/15230430.2000.12003342</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Hasholt&amp;Hagedorn,2000, Greenland Rivers SPM + dissolved + bed.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>He, Jie</author><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Dinis, Pedro</author><author>Yang, Shouye</author><author>Wang, Hua</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Provenance versus weathering control on sediment composition in tropical monsoonal climate (South China) - 1. Geochemistry and clay mineralogy</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>119860</pages><volume>558</volume><issue>June</issue><keywords><keyword>Clay mineralogy</keyword><keyword>Kaolinite as a weathering proxy</keyword><keyword>Pearl River catchment</keyword><keyword>Sand and mud geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Tropical monsoonal climate</keyword><keyword>Yangtze and Cathaysia blocks</keyword><keyword>αAl indices</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2020.119860</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://He et al. 2020, Pearl river sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2020.119860</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>This study presents an integrated mineralogical and geochemical database on mud and sand transported by the Pearl River (Zhujiang) and coastal rivers of SE China. Clay mineralogy and bulk-geochemistry of fluvial sediments are used to trace changes in weathering intensity across South China, a vast tropical to subtropical region characterized by a strong longitudinal rainfall gradient. The control of climate-induced weathering is manifest in the mineralogy and geochemistry of Pearl River mud, although mud and, to a greater extent, sand composition are also largely affected by the lithology of parent rocks. The depletion in mobile alkali and alkaline-earth metals increases steadily from the drier western part of the Pearl River catchment to the wetter eastern part and is most marked in easternmost tributaries of the Pearl River and in southern coastal rivers. Na and Ca are the most strongly depleted elements in Pearl River sediments, whereas the low concentration of Ca and Mg in river sand of coastal SE China also reflects the felsic character of parent rocks in the Cathaysia block. Eastward-increasing weathering conditions are most clearly highlighted by the progressive eastward increase in kaolinite across the Pearl River catchment, whereas the weathering effect in sand is blurred by quartz addition owing to widespread recycling of quartz-rich siliciclastic source rocks. This actualistic case study from a region characterized by monsoonal climate underscores the care that should be taken while inferring climatic conditions from the geochemical composition of sediments and sedimentary rocks, which is controlled by multiple geological factors including the felsic versus mafic character of parent rocks and the presence of extensive carbonate or siliciclastic covers in source areas. Most reliable indications are provided by the kaolinite/(illite+chlorite) ratio and by αAl indices for Na, Ca, Mg and Sr, which consistently increase eastward across South China thus paralleling the marked eastward increase in monsoonal precipitation towards the coast.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Hossain, H. M.Zakir</author><author>Kawahata, Hodaka</author><author>Roser, Barry P.</author><author>Sampei, Yoshikazu</author><author>Manaka, Takuya</author><author>Otani, Souya</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemical characteristics of modern river sediments in Myanmar and Thailand: Implications for provenance and weathering</title><secondary-title>Chemie der Erde</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemie der Erde</full-title></periodical><pages>443-458</pages><volume>77</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Myanmar and Thailand</keyword><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>Weathering and provenance</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2017</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier GmbH.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemer.2017.07.005</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Hossain et al. 2017, Myanmar &amp; Thailand rivers sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemer.2017.07.005</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The elemental composition of organic matter and the major and trace element compositions of stream sediments from Myanmar (Ayeyarwady and Sittaung rivers) and Thailand (Mekong and Chao Phraya rivers, and their tributaries) were determined to examine their distributions, provenance, and chemical weathering processes. Higher total organic carbon (TOC) and total nitrogen (TN) contents in the finer grained sediments indicate hydrodynamic energy may control their distributions. TOC/TN ratios indicate inputs of both aquatic macrophyte and higher vascular plant material to the river sediments. The major element abundances of the sediments are characterized by predominance of SiO2 in coarser fractions and a marked negative correlation with Al2O3, representing primary grain size primarily control on SiO2 content. Marked depletion of most labile elements (Na2O, CaO, K2O, Ba and Sr) relative to UCC (upper continental crust), indicate destruction of feldspar during chemical weathering in the source area or during transport. However, enrichment of some high field strength elements (Zr, Th, Ce and Y) relative to UCC and higher Zr/Sc ratios indicate moderate concentration of resistant heavy minerals in finer-grained samples. Discriminant diagrams and immobile trace element characteristics indicate that the Mekong, and Chao Phraya river sediments were largely derived from felsic sources with compositions close to typical rhyolite, dacite/granodiorite, UCC, I- and S-type granites. Relative enrichment of ferromagnesian elements (e.g. MgO, Cr, Ni) and high Cr/V and low Y/Ni ratios in Ayeyarwady and Sittaung sediments indicate the presence of a mafic or ultramafic component in their sources. The ICV (Index of Compositional Variability), CIA (Chemical Index of Alteration), PIA (Plagioclase Index of Alteration), αAl, Rb/Sr and K2O/Rb ratios indicate that the Ayeyarwady and Sittaung sediments record low to moderate degrees of chemical weathering in their source, compared to moderate to intense chemical weathering in the Mekong and Chao Phraya river basins. These results are compatible with existing major ion data for river waters collected at the same locations.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Krickov, Ivan V.</author><author>Lim, Artem G.</author><author>Manasypov, Rinat M.</author><author>Loiko, Sergey V.</author><author>Vorobyev, Sergey N.</author><author>Shevchenko, Vladimir P.</author><author>Dara, Olga M.</author><author>Gordeev, Vyacheslav V.</author><author>Pokrovsky, Oleg S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Major and trace elements in suspended matter of western Siberian rivers: First assessment across permafrost zones and landscape parameters of watersheds</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>429-450</pages><volume>269</volume><keywords><keyword>Micronutrient</keyword><keyword>Permafrost</keyword><keyword>River suspended matter</keyword><keyword>Season</keyword><keyword>Siberia</keyword><keyword>Toxicant</keyword><keyword>Trace metals</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gca.2019.11.005</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://krickov2019_WesternSibirianLowlands SuspendedMatterChComposition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>In contrast to good understanding of chemical composition of the river suspended matter (RSM) of large rivers, small rivers remain strongly understudied, despite the fact that they can provide valuable information on mechanisms of RSM generation and transport depending on key environmental parameters of the watershed. This is especially true for permafrost-affected boreal and subarctic territories, subjected to strong modification due to permafrost thaw and landscape changes under climate warming. We selected Earth's largest frozen peatland zone, the western Siberia Lowland (WSL) in order to test an impact of climate warming, permafrost thaw and landscape zone changes on riverine transport of particulate material from mainland to the Arctic Ocean. We sampled 33 small and medium size WSL rivers during spring flood, summer baseflow and autumn flood over a 1700 km gradient of climate and permafrost. Major and trace elements in particulate (&gt;0.45 µm) and dissolved (&lt;0.45 µm) fraction were analyzed. We hypothesize that future increase in active layer thickness and the change of dominant landscape from bogs and lakes to forest can be predicted via analyzing the actual pattern of RSM chemical composition across various permafrost zones and landscape parameters of WSL river watershed. We observed a minimum concentration of Li, Mg, Na, K, Rb, V, Cr, Zn, Cu, Co, Ni, Al, Ga, Y, REEs, Nb, W, Ti, Zr, Hf, Th and U in RSM collected from isolated and sporadic permafrost zones. Considering all seasons together, the presence of forest in the permafrost-bearing zone increased particulate concentrations of all alkalis and alkaline-earth elements, B, As, Nb, Mn, Co, Al, Ga, REEs, Ti, Zr, Hf, Th. This is consistent with element mobilization from mineral horizons that become available for interacting with soil fluids under forested regions. Lakes retained particulate alkaline-earths, Fe, Mn, Co, trivalent and tetravalent hydrolysates (TE3+, TE4+). The concentration of lithogenic low-soluble elements (TE3+, TE4+) in the RSM strongly increased with the river size (watershed area). Compared to the world RSM average, the WSL rivers exhibited lower concentrations of all elements except Mn and P and a low share of suspended elements relative to total (suspended + dissolved) forms of trace metals and of low-mobility (lithogenic) elements. Likely reasons for these features are: (i) low runoff and low RSM concentration as there is no rock and mineral substrate exposed to physical weathering in WSL peatland; (ii) organic, rather than mineral, nature of surrounding “solid” substrates and as a result, organic rather than silicate nature of RSM, and (iii) high DOC and Fe concentration leading to high concentrations of typically low-solubilty elements in the dissolved (&lt;0.45 µm) fraction due to colloids. From a climate warming perspective, the increase in active layer thickness and involvement of mineral horizons into soil fluid migration in discontinuous to continuous permafrost zone will likely increase the share of particulate fraction in total element transport for many soluble (labile) elements and also lithogenic elements in WSL rivers. At the same time, permafrost boundary shift northward may decrease particulate concentrations of most major and TE in rivers of discontinuous permafrost zone. The lake drainage and forest colonization of tundra and bogs in the permafrost-affected part of WSL may increase the concentration of alkali and alkaline-earth elements, divalent metals and trivalent and tetravalent hydrolysates. As a result, export of particulate metal micronutrients and toxicants from the WSL territory to the Arctic Ocean may increase.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lartiges, B. S.</author><author>Deneux-Mustin, S.</author><author>Villemin, G.</author><author>Mustin, C.</author><author>Barrès, O.</author><author>Chamerois, M.</author><author>Gerard, B.</author><author>Babut, M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Composition, structure and size distribution of suspended particulates from the Rhine River</title><secondary-title>Water Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Research</full-title></periodical><pages>808-816</pages><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Aggregation</keyword><keyword>Exopolymeric substances</keyword><keyword>Fluvial suspended matter</keyword><keyword>Particulate</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2001</year></dates><accession-num>11228980</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0043-1354(00)00293-1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Lartiges et al. 2000, Rhine, FRANCE, SPM composition and structure (high calcite).pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Fluvial suspended particulates collected from the Rhine River were investigated in terms of composition, structure and size distribution. Elemental analysis and Diffuse Reflectance Infrared Spectroscopy reveal that most particulate organic matter is formed from material derived from microorganisms. Transmission Electron Microscopy observations on resin-embedded samples and structural characterization from break-up experiments, show that fluvial particulate matter should be viewed as fractal aggregates organized by bacterial exopolymeric substances. The shape of particulate size distribution suggests that the formation and dynamics of suspended particulate matter are controlled mainly by physical processes. Finally, particulate growth and structure are consistent with a cluster-cluster aggregation scheme. © 2001 Elsevier Science Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Le Pera, Emilia</author><author>Sorriso-Valvo, Marino</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Weathering, erosion and sediment composition in a high-gradient river, Calabria, Italy</title><secondary-title>Earth Surface Processes and Landforms</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth Surface Processes and Landforms</full-title></periodical><pages>277-292</pages><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Calabria</keyword><keyword>Erosion</keyword><keyword>Italy</keyword><keyword>River</keyword><keyword>Sediment</keyword><keyword>Weathering</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2000</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1002/(SICI)1096-9837(200003)25:3&lt;277::AID-ESP79&gt;3.0.CO;2-Z</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Le Pera &amp; Sorriso-Valvo 2000, Calabria river italy, sediment composition &amp; erosion.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Source rock lithology and immediate modifying processes, such as chemical weathering and mechanical erosion, are primary controls on fluvial sediment supply. Sand composition and Chemical Index of Alteration (CIA) of parent rocks, soil and fluvial sand of the Savuto River watershed, Calabria (Italy), were used to evaluate the modifications of source rocks through different sections of the basin, characterized by different geomorphic processes, in a sub-humid Mediterranean climate. The headwaters, with gentle topography, produce a coarse-grained sediment load derived from deeply weathered gneiss, having sand of quartzofeldspathic composition, compositionally very different from in situ degraded bedrock. Maximum estimated CIA values suggest that source rock has been affected significantly by weathering, and it testifies to a climatic threshold on the destruction of the bedrock. The mid-course has steeper slopes and a deeply incised valley; bedrock consists of mica-schist and phyllite with a very thin regolith, which provides large cobble to very coarse sand sediments to the main channel. Slope instability, with an areal incidence of over 40 per cent, largely supplies detritus to the main channel. Sand-sized detritus of soil and fluvial sand is lithic. Estimated CIA value testifies to a significant weathering of the bedrock too, even if in this part of the drainage basin steeper slopes allow erosion to exceed chemical weathering. The lower course has a braided pattern and sediment load is coarse to medium-fine grained. The river cuts across Palaeozoic crystalline rocks and Miocene siliciclastic deposits. Sand-sized detritus, contributed from these rocks and homogenized by transport processes, has been found in the quartzolithic distal samples. Field and laboratory evidence indicates that landscape development was the result of extensive weathering during the last postglacial temperature maximum in the headwaters, and of mass-failure and fluvial erosional processes in the mid- and low course. Copyright (C) 2000 John Wiley and Sons, Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Lučić, Mavro</author><author>Jurina, Irena</author><author>Ščančar, Janez</author><author>Mikac, Nevenka</author><author>Vdović, Neda</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sedimentological and geochemical characterization of river suspended particulate matter (SPM) sampled by time-integrated mass flux sampler (TIMS) in the Sava River (Croatia)</title><secondary-title>Journal of Soils and Sediments</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Soils and Sediments</full-title></periodical><pages>989-1004</pages><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Suspended matter</keyword><keyword>The Sava River</keyword><keyword>Time-integrated sampler</keyword><keyword>Trace elements</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2019</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s11368-018-2104-2</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Lučić2019_SPM Sava River-DanubeTrib, Croatia.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Purpose: Suspended particulate matter (SPM) plays a crucial role in the transport of natural and anthropogenic substances. However, obtaining a representative sample and a substantial amount of SPM in rivers, where the flux and quantity of SPM are highly episodic, can be a challenging task. To collect a sufficient quantity of SPM for detailed sedimentological and geochemical analysis, a time-integrated mass flux sampler (TIMS) was used for the sampling in a medium size river (the Sava River, Croatia). Materials and methods: Sampling was conducted in August and October 2014, and February and May 2015 under different discharge conditions. The SPM collected by TIMS was characterized with respect to its particle size distribution (PSD), mineral content, and geochemical composition. Results and discussion: PSD analysis identified silt as a dominant size fraction in all samples except in May 2015 when sand prevailed; subsequent chemical dispersion of samples revealed flocculation as the main factor responsible for the resulting PSD. The mineralogical composition of the SPM was quite constant (quartz, calcite, dolomite, feldspar, illite/muscovite, kaolinite), but the contribution of particular mineral varied depending on the sampling period. In May 2015, unusually high calcite content was determined. Though the dominant source is still uncertain, a portion of calcite is likely detrital in origin. Geochemical analyses of collected material revealed significant anthropogenic input of ecotoxic elements (Ni, As, Cr, Pb, Bi, Cd, Zn, Sb) primarily associated with the fine fraction of the Sava River SPM. Conclusions: A considerable amount of the SPM was collected by TIMS, both during high and low river discharge. Sedimentological analyses of the Sava River SPM suggested the input of material from various sources during different river regimes. Geochemical composition of the SPM followed its sedimentological characteristics—preferential adsorption of trace elements to fine-grained clay mineral particles was documented. Some processes inside TIMS were observed during this investigation—the suspended material captured inside the sampler underwent additional changes. The flocculation of the colloidal material instigated by algal bloom was observed.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>MANICKAM, S.</author><author>BARBAROUX, L.</author><author>OTTMANN, F.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Composition and mineralogy of suspended sediment in the fluvio‐estuarine zone of the Loire River, France</title><secondary-title>Sedimentology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Sedimentology</full-title></periodical><pages>721-741</pages><volume>32</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1985</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/j.1365-3091.1985.tb00484.x</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://manickam1985, Loire River Sediment composition &amp; mineralogy.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The fluvio‐tidal transition of suspended sediment in terms of mineralogy and composition in the Loire River drainage basin, the largest French river basin, was investigated in the fluvial zone at Montjean and in the tidal zone at Mauves‐Thouaré, for a complete seasonal cycle. At Montjean, where the river experiences unidirectional flow, the composition and mineralogy (especially clays and clay minerals) of river suspended material (RSM) are governed by the river discharge, upstream contributions, climatic conditions and microbiological activities. However, due to reversing tidal and river currents at Thouaré, in the zone of tidal dynamics, these relations are changed. In the downstream direction sand and clay content in the RSM decrease while the silt content increases. Among clay minerals, between these two observation stations, montmorillonite remains constant, kaolinite diminishes, and the other minerals increase downstream. Combustible material (organic) and nitrate (NO3) contents in the RSM increase whereas the phosphate (PO43‐) and CaCO3 contents decline considerably during transport. At the head of the tidal zone, where the river flow encounters the tidal influence, there is a relatively stationary water mass (tidal slack) where sands, clays, phosphate, carbonate and silica are deposited by physical and chemical processes. Physical sedimentation takes place by simple gravitational deposition (sands), and by sorting and complicated differential settling (clays); chemical sedimentation takes place by precipitation (calcite‐CaCO3; apatite‐Ca5 (PO4)3 (OH,F,Cl); coagulation of dissolved silica‐SiO2) in connection with seasonal algal bloom and eutrophic events. Copyright © 1985, Wiley Blackwell. All rights reserved</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Martin, Candace E.</author><author>McCulloch, Malcolm T.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Nd-Sr isotopic and trace element geochemistry of river sediments and soils in a fertilized catchment, New South Wales, Australia</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>287-305</pages><volume>63</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0016-7037(98)00308-1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Martin &amp; McCulloch 1998, New South Wales Rivers, Australia, Soil-SPM-Rock ME, TE &amp; NdSr.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Neodymium and strontium isotopes and a suite of trace elements have been used to distinguish between the various sources of particulate loads and soils in a major catchment of the Murray-Darling drainage system, the largest river in Australia. One of the goals was to estimate additions of Sr and rare earth elements of anthropogenic (fertilizer) origin to the natural catchment sources to the soils and streams. Among possible sediment sources, Tertiary basalts and Paleozoic metagraywackes have the lowest 87Sr/86Sr and highest ε(Nd), whereas Paleozoic metapelitic rocks have negative ε(Nd) and the highest 87Sr/86Sr. Phosphate fertilizers have strongly negative ε(Nd) and 87Sr/86Sr similar to Tertiary seawater. Soils formed on basalt and metagraywacke have compositions that are shifted toward higher 87Sr/86Sr and lower ε(Nd) than their parent rocks. REE patterns and elemental ratios such as Nd/P are also distinctive between fertilizer and natural catchment sources. Reservoir sediment from the upper catchment have isotopic and trace element compositions that confirm that the dominant source of stream particulates is from basalt soils in the steep upland part of the catchment. Mixing calculations based on isotopic and elemental compositions for reservoir sediment in the upper catchment are consistent with less than 0.2% bulk addition by mass of fertilizer to the natural sediment source. The isotopic compositions of soils in less easily eroded portions of the upper catchment reflect the addition of a component to the soil which is interpreted to be wind-blown dust, derived either from Paleozoic granitoids that dominate the lower regions of the catchment or from more distal westerly sources. Sediment from the lower catchment requires that the dominant source below the reservoir is derived from Paleozoic granitoid and metapelitic rocks of the New England fold belt. The lower catchment sediments show no definitive evidence of either basalt or fertilizer input. Natural sources dominate the particulate loads in these streams.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Martins, O</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Flux of particulate inorganic matter through the Niger river into the Atlantic ocean</title><secondary-title>Netherlands Journal of Sea Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Netherlands Journal of Sea Research</full-title></periodical><pages>91-97</pages><volume>22</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1988</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Martins 1988, Niger river, particulate fluxes to atlantic ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mbaye, Mamadou L.</author><author>Gaye, Amadou T.</author><author>Spitzy, Alejandro</author><author>Dähnke, Kirstin</author><author>Afouda, Abel</author><author>Gaye, Birgit</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Seasonal and spatial variation in suspended matter, organic carbon, nitrogen, and nutrient concentrations of the Senegal River in West Africa</title><secondary-title>Limnologica</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Limnologica</full-title></periodical><pages>1-13</pages><volume>57</volume><keywords><keyword>Dissolved organic carbon</keyword><keyword>Nutrients</keyword><keyword>Particulate organic carbon</keyword><keyword>Senegal River</keyword><keyword>Suspended matter</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier GmbH.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.limno.2015.12.003</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://mbaye2016_SenegalRiver-DischargePOC.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.limno.2015.12.003</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The Senegal River is of intermediate size accommodating at present about 3.5 million inhabitants in its catchment. Its upstream tributaries flow through different climatic zones from the wet tropics in the source area in Guinea to the dry Sahel region at the border between Senegal and Mauritania. Total suspended matter, particulate and dissolved organic carbon and nitrogen as well as nutrient concentrations were determined during the dry and wet seasons at 19 locations from the up- to downstream river basin. The aims of the study were to evaluate the degree of human interference, to determine the dissolved and particulate river discharges into the coastal sea and to supply data to validate model results. Statistical analyses showed that samples from the wet and dry season are significantly different in composition and that the upstream tributaries differ mainly in their silicate and suspended matter contents. Nutrient concentrations are relatively low in the river basin, indicating low human impact. Increasing nitrate concentrations, however, show the growing agriculture in the irrigated downstream areas. Particulate organic matter is dominated by C4 plants during the wet season and by aquatic plankton during the dry season. The total suspended matter (TSM) discharge at the main gauging station Bakel was about 1.93Tgyr-1 which is in the range of the only available literature data from the 1980s. The calculated annual discharges of particulate organic carbon (POC), dissolved organic carbon (DOC) and dissolved organic nitrogen (DON) are 55.8Ggyr-1, 54.1Ggyr-1, and 5.3Ggyr-1, respectively. These first estimates from the Senegal River need to be verified by further studies.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Mihai, S. A.</author><author>Mather, J. D.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Role of mineralogical structure of sediments in accumulation of radionuclides and trace elements</title><secondary-title>Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Radioanalytical and Nuclear Chemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>425-430</pages><volume>256</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2003</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1023/A:1024587313309</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://mihai &amp; mather 2003, Danube river, Romania, Sediment composition &amp; radionuclides.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Similar distributions for 238U, 232Th, 226Ra, 210Po, 238,239,240Pu, 137Cs and trace elements were obtained in sediment samples collected along the Romanian sector of the Danube River and the Black Sea coast during 1994. The radionuclide and trace element accumulation in the investigated samples is discussed with respect to their geochemical behavior and the mineralogical structure of the samples. The latter, investigated by X-ray diffraction and cation exchange capacity of the same samples, proves to be an important factor in the selection of sampling sites for monitoring the pollution of river basins and the sea.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Nagano, T.</author><author>Yanase, N.</author><author>Tsuduki, K.</author><author>Nagao, S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Particulate and dissolved elemental loads in the Kuji River related to discharge rate</title><secondary-title>Environment International</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environment International</full-title></periodical><pages>649-658</pages><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><keywords><keyword>Chemical species</keyword><keyword>Fluvial transport</keyword><keyword>Major elements</keyword><keyword>Suspended particulate matter</keyword><keyword>Trace elements</keyword><keyword>Water discharge</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2003</year></dates><accession-num>12504162</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0160-4120(02)00105-8</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://nagano et al. 2003, Kuji River, Japan, SPM and dissolved loads.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>In order to investigate influences of discharge rates on fluvial transport behavior of elements in the Kuji River, Japan, suspended and dissolved phase concentrations in the river water were measured together with the water flow rates. The concentrations of suspended particulate matter (SPM) increased by two or three orders of magnitude with the water discharge, and also had seasonal variations. Adsorptive elements or heavy metal elements, which tend to form insoluble compounds, were present generally as suspended forms in the river waters, and their dissolved form concentrations tended to increase with the water discharge. On the other hand, non-adsorptive elements such as alkali and alkaline-earth elements were present as dissolved forms under a normal flow rate condition, but equivalent quantity of suspended species also occurred under a high flow condition. In this case, the dissolved form concentrations decreased with the water discharge. Characterization of SPM with analyses of chemical compositions, scanning electron microscopy (SEM) and X-ray diffractometry (XRD) indicated that clay mineral such as montmorillonite would be the main carrier material of trace and major elements during the fluvial transport in the Kuji River. Variations of contents of selected elements in SPM with the water discharge indicated that river bottom sediments, which are probably potential sources of SPM added due to high water flow rates, would be different in chemical compositions from SPM floating under a normal flow condition. Variations of chemical compositions of SPM as well as of suspended or dissolved form concentrations of elements in the river waters were formulated as a function of the water discharge rates. © 2002 Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Navrátil, Tomáš</author><author>Rohovec, Jan</author><author>Žák, Karel</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Floodplain sediments of the 2002 catastrophic flood at the Vltava (Moldau) River and its tributaries: Mineralogy, chemical composition, and post-sedimentary evolution</title><secondary-title>Environmental Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environmental Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>399-412</pages><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>2002 Catastrophic flood</keyword><keyword>Berounka River</keyword><keyword>Czech Republic</keyword><keyword>Floodplain sediments</keyword><keyword>Vltava (Moldau) River</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2008</year></dates><isbn>0025400711</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s00254-007-1178-8</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Navrátil et al. 2008_Moldau, Elbe, Czech, Flood sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Fine-grained floodplain sediments of the catastrophic 2002 flood deposited along the lower reaches of the Berounka and Vltava Rivers, Czech Republic, were not highly contaminated with heavy metals and other toxic elements. This is due to the dominantly mineral character of the sediments (Ctot in the range 3.97-5.01%, relatively low content of clay minerals), and due to the very high degree of contamination dilution by eroded pre-industrial non-contaminated floodplain sediments. Despite this high degree of dilution, the influence of the small Litavka River, draining the historical Pb-Zn-Ag Příbram ore region, is well visible. The Litavka River is one of important sources of Pb and Zn contamination in the whole Berounka-Vltava-Labe river system. The 2002 flood sediments deposited in the floodplain of the Berounka and Vltava Rivers show poor vertical chemical zoning, except for some components enriched in the uppermost layer by precipitation from evaporated pore-water contained in the mud, i.e. secondary carbonate. The content of Ccarb of the sediments (0.05-0.15%) is partly represented by this secondary carbonate, which is later leached by rainwater, and partly by fragments of river mollusk shells. A majority of the heavy metals contained in sediments can be readily leached by diluted acids, and to a much smaller degree by rainwater. © 2008 Springer-Verlag.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Négrel, Philippe</author><author>Grosbois, Cécile</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Changes in chemical and 87Sr/86Sr signature distribution patterns of suspended matter and bed sediments in the upper Loire river basin (France)</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>231-249</pages><volume>156</volume><issue>1-4</issue><keywords><keyword>87Sr/86Sr</keyword><keyword>Authigenic calcite</keyword><keyword>Bed load</keyword><keyword>Loire river</keyword><keyword>Suspended matter</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0009-2541(98)00182-X</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Negrel &amp; Grosbois, 1999, Upper Loire River, SPM &amp;&amp; bed sediment composition &amp; mineralogy.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The mineralogy of the suspended particulate matter (SPM) transported by the upper Loire river consists mainly of quartz and K-feldspar during periods of high river flow, with an increase in calcite concentration during periods of low flow. Concurrently, large fluctuations are observed in the levels of CaO and Fe2O3, the main oxides present in the SPM along with SiO2. The analysed trace elements also fluctuate significantly. The bed sediments (BS) have a similar oxide content to the SPM, but lower Zn and Pb levels and higher Zr levels. Fluctuations in the chemical-element concentrations with river discharge are related to fluctuation in the mineral assemblages present in the SPM. Thus K, Ti and Rb levels increase with increasing in K-feldspar abundance during high flow, and Ca and Sr levels decrease with increasing discharge due to a decrease in calcite abundance. These mineralogical and chemical variations relate to different sources of sediments under different flow conditions-sources that can be distinguished by Sr isotopic study. The Sr isotopic composition fluctuates according to the rate of river discharge; i.e., the 87Sr/86Sr ratio increases with increasing discharge and reaches a maximum with peak flow, and vice versa. The 87Sr/86Sr ratio also increases with the combined increase in K-feldspar abundance and decrease in calcite abundance. These similarities suggest the existence of at least two particulate-matter reservoirs, one with detrital silicates and the other with carbonates. Finally, the relationship between the 87Sr/86Sr ratios in the suspended and dissolved loads suggests the coexistence of authigenic calcite in the carbonate reservoir. The SPM flow is related to a specific mechanical erosion rate over the whole Loire watershed ranging from 9 to 23 t km-2 yr-1. During the survey at Orleans, the SPM flow of the Loire river was 37 · 104 t yr-1, providing an estimate of the specific erosion rate of around 9.8 t km-2 yr-1. From the shift in the SPM flux between the sampling point and the mouth of the Loire river and the divergence in the mean annual discharge, a calculation was made of the input of solid matter by the tributaries and by supplementary erosion processes along the river.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ödman, Fredrik</author><author>Ruth, Thomas</author><author>Pontér, Christer</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Validation of a field filtration technique for characterization of suspended particulate matter from freshwater. Part I. Major elements</title><secondary-title>Applied Geochemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Applied Geochemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>301-317</pages><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0883-2927(98)00050-X</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Oedman et al. 1999_Swedish rivers - Validation SPM filtering.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>A field filtration method for the concentration and separation of suspended particulate matter (SPM) from freshwater systems for subsequent determination of major elements (Si, Al, Ca, Fe, Mn, Mg, Na, K, P, Ti and S) is validated with respect to precision and bias. The validation comprises the whole procedure including filtration, sample digestion and instrumental analysis. The method includes two digestion procedures (microwave acid digestion and alkali fusion) in combination with inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry (ICP-AES). Total concentrations of the elements have been determined in suspended particulate matter from lake and river water with low levels of suspended solids (&lt; 2 mg l-1 DW), and a wide range of element concentrations. The precision of the method including filtration, digestion and instrumental determination ranges between 10 and 14% RSD for most elements on a dry weight basis. Non-detectable concentrations of some elements are reported due to small differences between blank filter levels and the amounts of elements present on the filters after sampling. The calculated sums of main inorganic components, expressed as oxides, ranges between 94.0 and 98.0% ash weight. The method limits of detection range between 3 and 100 μg, as estimated from the blank filter samples TheSe detection limits are 3-1000 times higher compared to the corresponding instrumental (ICP-AES) limits of detection. A better knowledge of the mechanisms of filter clogging in sampling of suspended matter is important in order to extend the applicability of the method. For the sample types investigated in this study, the amount of inorganic material in the suspended particulate matter (SPM) seems to be the most important factor controlling the maximum volume of filterable water, and Fe is presumably the most important clogging regulating parameter in the group of elements included in the inorganic matter. A critical evaluation of the indirect method of calculating concentrations in SPM as the difference between unfiltered-digested and filtered subsamples is also included.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ollivier, P.</author><author>Hamelin, B.</author><author>Radakovitch, O.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Seasonal variations of physical and chemical erosion: A three-year survey of the Rhone River (France)</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>907-927</pages><volume>74</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2010</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gca.2009.10.037</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Ollivier et al. 2010, Rhone River, France, 3 year survey sediment chemistry at arles.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Numerous studies of weathering fluxes have been carried out on major world rivers during the last decade, to estimate CO2 consumption rates, landscape evolution and global erosion rates. For obvious logistical reasons, most of these studies were based on large scale investigations carried out on short timescales. By comparison, much less effort has been devoted to long term monitoring, as a means to verify the temporal variability of the average characteristics, their trends, and the representativeness of short-term investigations. Here we report the results of a three-year survey (November 2000 to December 2003) of the major and trace element composition of dissolved and suspended matter in the lower Rhone River (France), the largest river of the Mediterranean area. Subsurface water samples were collected in Arles, about 48 km upstream of the estuary, twice a month routinely, and at higher frequency during flood events. During each flood event, the suspended particulate matter (SPM) show the usual trend of clockwise hysteresis with higher SPM concentrations on the rising limb of the flood than at the same discharge on the falling limb. We show that the annual average SPM flux of the Rhone River to the Mediterranean Sea (7.3 ± 0.6 × 106 tons yr-1) was largely controlled by the flood events (83% of the solid discharge occurred in less than 12% of the time), and that the precision on the total output flux depends strongly on the precise monitoring of SPM variations during the floods. The chemical composition of water and SPM are characterized by the predominance of Ca2+ due to the abundance of carbonate rocks in the Rhone watershed. Chemical budgets have been calculated to derive the contributions of atmospheric deposition, carbonate, silicate and evaporite weathering, and anthropogenic inputs. The chemical weathering rate of carbonates is estimated to be 89 ± 5 t km-2 yr-1 compared to 14.4 ± 3 t km-2 yr-1 from silicates. By contrast, the physical erosion rate of silicates is about 51 t km-2 yr-1 against 19 t km-2 yr-1 for carbonates. The steady-state model of Gaillardet et al. (1995) has been applied to the chemical composition of dissolved and solid products. The results show that the Rhone River currently exports much less material than produced at steady-state by weathering in its watershed. The sediment flux inferred from the steady-state calculation (21-56 × 106 t yr-1) is on the same order as that estimated in literature for the 19th and the beginning of the 20th centuries. This imbalance may suggest that the Rhone is under a transient erosion regime following climate change (i.e. significant decrease of the flooding frequency since the beginning of the 19th century). On the other hand, the imbalance may also be due to the trapping of alluvion by the numerous dams on the river and its tributaries. Our data corroborate with previous studies that suggest a strong coupling between chemical and physical erosion fluxes, during the hydrological seasonal cycle of the Rhone River. The correlation between physical and chemical transport rates is, however, clearly different from that reported for global annual averages in large world rivers. © 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pang, Hongli</author><author>Pan, Baotian</author><author>Garzanti, Eduardo</author><author>Gao, Hongshan</author><author>Zhao, Xin</author><author>Chen, Dianbao</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mineralogy and geochemistry of modern Yellow River sediments: Implications for weathering and provenance</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>76-86</pages><volume>488</volume><issue>222</issue><keywords><keyword>Arid climate</keyword><keyword>Chemical weathering</keyword><keyword>Clay mineral assemblages</keyword><keyword>Provenance analysis</keyword><keyword>Sedimentary geochemistry</keyword><keyword>Yellow River</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2018</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2018.04.010</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Pang et al. 2018, Yellow River, China, bulk sediment mineralogy and geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2018.04.010</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>This study illustrates the textural, mineralogical and geochemical signatures of sediments from the upper Yellow River. Sediments of major tributaries have also been examined to study the influence of provenance, weathering intensity, and hydraulic sorting on the spatial compositional variability of sediments. Similarly to floodplain sediments, riverbed deposits are strongly depleted in MgO and Na2O, and enriched in CaO and Si2O relative to the upper-continental-crust standard. The pattern of rare earth elements (REE) indicates LREE enrichment and negative Eu anomaly (Eu/Eu* = 0.54–0.68). Low CIA (Chemical Index of Alteration) values indicate that the sediments from the trunk-river channel, floodplain, and major tributaries have not experienced intense chemical weathering in arid to semi-arid climatic conditions. The distribution of chemical elements shows a significant increase of Zr and Hf with coarsening of grain-size, whereas Rb, Ni, and V are associated with finer sediment fractions supplied by adjacent dune fields and tributaries. The Al/Si ratio (a proxy for grain size) correlates positively with CIA, Fe2O3, MgO, and K2O, but not with Na2O, reflecting grain-size control. Clay mineral assemblages in the upper Yellow River and in tributaries draining the Loess Plateau (e.g., Qingshui and Zuli Rivers) are dominated by illite and chlorite, whereas the abundance of smectite characterizes the middle reaches of the Yellow River and the Ten tributaries draining the Ordos Plateau.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pehlivan, Rustem</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The effect of weathering in the Buyukmelen River basin on the geochemistry of suspended and bed sediments and the hyrogeochemical characteristics of river water, Duzce, Turkey</title><secondary-title>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences</full-title></periodical><pages>62-75</pages><volume>39</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Bed sediment</keyword><keyword>Hydrogeochemistry</keyword><keyword>River water</keyword><keyword>Suspended sediment</keyword><keyword>Turkey</keyword><keyword>Water quality</keyword><keyword>Weathering</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2010</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.jseaes.2010.02.011</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Pehlivan2010_Buyukmelen River, Turkey, TDS +SPM mineralogy+chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2010.02.011</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The Buyukmelen River is expected to be a water source that can supply the drinking water needs of Istanbul until 2040. The drinking and utility water needs of Istanbul are to transport water from the Buyukmelen River to Istanbul via pipeline and pump it into the Alibeykoy and Omerli reservoirs when their water levels drop. The Buyukmelen River is located in the province of Duzce in 170km east of Istanbul and its water basin is approximately 2250km2. The Buyukmelen River flows muddy in the rainy season and into the Black Sea. The chemical compositions of natural waters alter due to interaction with geological formations, physical and chemical weathering of various rocks and the effects of mining and agricultural production. A research was conducted at the Buyukmelen River basin to determine the effects of hydrological processes. Therefore, the samples of rocks, soil, stream water, suspended and bed sediment were collected from the Buyukmelen River basin. Geochemical and water chemistry analyses of samples were performed at ALS Chemex laboratories, Canada. The bed sediments contain quartz, calcite, plagioclase, amphibole and clay minerals. The clay minerals in the suspended and bed sediment samples are kaolinite, smectite and illite. The water samples collected from the Aksu, Kucukmelen, Asarsu and Ugursuyu streams and the Buyukmelen River in winter (December 2005) and summer (June 2006) periods are rich in Ca and HCO3 ions. The ions most abundant in rainfall sample are HCO3 and Na. The ion compositions of surface waters have increased due to the weathering of limestone, agglomerate and volcanic sandstones, light acidic rainfall, semi-arid Black Sea climate in the Buyukmelen basin. The suspended sediment amount of the Buyukmelen River in the rainy season (December 2005) is 174mg/l. According to the water contamination regulation of Turkey, the Buyukmelen Rivers belongs to quality class 4 based on Al ion and to quality class 3 based on Fe ion in winter period, and to quality class 2 based on Mn concentration in summer period. Chemical index of alteration (CIA) indices observed in the suspended and bed sediments (average of 55) suggest that their source area underwent moderate degrees of chemical weathering processes. According to Upper Continental Crust (UCC) values, the suspended sediment was rich in elements such as Fe2O3, CaO, MgO, MnO, TiO2, P2O5, V, Cr, Co, Cu, Zn, As, Cd, Sb, Hg and Pb. The element concentrations of the suspended sediments were related to size fractionation, mainly of clay content. The mentioned enrichment was contributed by agglomerate, basalt, volcanic sandstone and graywacke from rocks in the study area. Source of ions such as Al, Fe, Mn, Ba, Cr, Co, Cu, Ni, Ti and Hg and major in the Buyukmelen River is interaction with rocks such as the agglomerate, basalt, andesite, volcanic sandstone and graywacke. As suggested by Singh et al. (2005), before weathering of some rocks in the Buyukmelen River basin, it was determined that they were graywacke and literanite based on the geochemistry of the suspended and bed sediments. © 2010 Elsevier Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pekka, Larisa</author><author>Ingri, Johan</author><author>Widerlund, Anders</author><author>Mokrotovarova, Olga</author><author>Riabtseva, Margarita</author><author>Öhlander, Björn</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of the Kola River, northwestern Russia</title><secondary-title>Applied Geochemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Applied Geochemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>1975-1995</pages><volume>19</volume><issue>12</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.apgeochem.2004.05.008</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Pekka et al. 2004, Kola River, NW Russia, SPM + diss geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The Kola River in the northern part of the Kola Peninsula, northwestern Russia, flows into the Barents Sea via the Kola Bay. The river is a unique place for reproduction of salmon and an important source of drinking water for more than 500,000 people in Murmansk and the surrounding municipalities. To evaluate the environmental status of the Kola River water, sampling of the dissolved (&lt;0.22 μm) and suspended (&gt;0.22 μm) phases was performed at 12 sites along the Kola River and its tributaries during 2001 and 2002. Major (Ca, K, Mg, Na, S, Si, HCO3 and Cl) and trace (Al, As, Ba, Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, Fe, Mn, Mo, Ni, Pb, Sr, Ti, and Zn) elements, total and particulate organic C (TOC and POC), N and P were analysed. Comparison with the boreal pristine Kalix River, Northern Sweden, shows that, except for Na, Cl, Al, Cu and Ni, which exceed the concentrations in the Kalix River by as much as 2-3 times, the levels of other major and trace elements are close to or even below the levels in the Kalix River. However, the results also demonstrate that pollutants from the three major sources: (1) the Cu-Ni smelter in Monchegorsk, (2) the open-pit Fe mine and ore concentration plant in Olenegorsk, and (3) the Varlamov, the Medveziy and the Zemlanoy creeks, draining the area of the large agricultural enterprises in the lower part of the watershed, have a major influence on the water quality of the Kola River. © 2004 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pettine, M.</author><author>Camusso, M.</author><author>Martinotti, W.</author><author>Marchetti, R.</author><author>Passino, R.</author><author>Queirazza, G.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Soluble and particulate metals in the Po River: Factors affecting concentrations and partitioning</title><secondary-title>Science of the Total Environment, The</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Science of the Total Environment, The</full-title></periodical><pages>243-265</pages><volume>145</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Freshwater</keyword><keyword>Heavy metals</keyword><keyword>Partitioning</keyword><keyword>Transport</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1994</year></dates><accession-num>8023132</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/0048-9697(94)90118-X</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://pettine1994_Po, Italy, river and estuary SPM composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Fourteen metals (Ca, Mg, Al, Fe, Mn, Ba, As, Cd, Co, Cr, Cu, Ni, Pb and Zn) were monitored over a 2-year period in the waters of the lower Po River. Concentrations in the dissolved and particulate phases were measured, thus constructing a large database on metal variability. The influence of flow and solid transport on dissolved, particulate and total metal concentrations is discussed. In addition to flow rate and solid content, biological processes seem to be one of the main factors affecting concentrations in the dissolved phase, while the inorganic components of solids seem to control metal concentration in suspended matter. Data on partitioning of metals between the dissolved and particulate phases are presented, together with related information on the affinity sequence of metals for the particulate phase, and the influence of solid load on the modes of metal transport. © 1994.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Pokrovsky, O. S.</author><author>Viers, J.</author><author>Shirokova, L. S.</author><author>Shevchenko, V. P.</author><author>Filipov, A. S.</author><author>Dupré, B.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Dissolved, suspended, and colloidal fluxes of organic carbon, major and trace elements in the Severnaya Dvina River and its tributary</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>136-149</pages><volume>273</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Arctic Ocean</keyword><keyword>Colloids</keyword><keyword>Fluxes</keyword><keyword>River</keyword><keyword>Speciation</keyword><keyword>Suspended matter</keyword><keyword>Trace element</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2010</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2010.02.018</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Pokrovsky et al. 2010, S Divina SPM + Diss.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2010.02.018</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The chemical status of major and trace elements (TE) and organic carbon (OC) has been studied in the Severnaya Dvina and Pinega rivers draining granitic moraine, carbonate and sedimentary deposits of the Arkhangelsk region (NW Russia, the White Sea basin of the Arctic Ocean). Sampling was performed during winter and summer baseflow seasons and during the spring flood (2007-2008). Size separation procedure included on-site filtration through 5μm, 0.22μm, 100, 10 and 1kDa, and dialysis through 1kDa and 10kDa pore-size membranes. The organic carbon concentration in &quot;truly&quot; dissolved form (&lt;1kDa) does not depend on rock lithology or season, being on average equal to 5.0±1.4mg/L. Our observations may suggest the presence of two types of organic matter pool: i) allochtonous large-size colloids formed by lixiviation from upper soil horizons and ii) autochthonous (aquatic) small molecular-size substances, probably linked to bacterial and phytoplankton exudates. The total dissolved concentration of colloidal TE correlates with OC and Fe contents, being highest during the spring flood and lowest in winter time. There are two different patterns of TE colloidal status during different periods of the year, depending on their association with the organic or organo-mineral constituents of the colloidal matter pool.Trace and major element concentrations in the suspended matter of the River Severnaya Dvina were measured during different seasons over three years of observation. Based on collected data, we evaluate here, for the first time, the seasonal fluxes of major and trace elements in the suspended (&gt;0.22μm), total dissolved (&lt;0.22μm) and colloidal (1kDa-0.22μm) forms. On an annual basis, there is a significant contribution (≥30%) of conventionally dissolved species (&lt;0.22μm) to the overall flux of usually weakly mobile elements such as the divalent transition metals, Cd, Pb, V, Y, all REEs, Zr, Hf and Th. The transport of these insoluble elements occurs essentially in colloidal form. The spring flood occurring in May provides between 30 and 60% of the total annual dissolved and suspended flux of many insoluble trace elements (Fe, Co, Ni, Cr, Y, all REEs, Cd, Pb, Zr, Hf and Th). We argue that trace element fluxes in Arctic rivers are often characterized by a high proportion of total dissolved matter (&lt;0.22μm) compared to suspended particulates, due mostly to the large contribution of organically-bound colloidal forms. © 2010 Elsevier B.V.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Prabakaran, K.</author><author>Nagarajan, R.</author><author>Eswaramoorthi, S.</author><author>Anandkumar, A.</author><author>Franco, F. Merlin</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Environmental significance and geochemical speciation of trace elements in Lower Baram River sediments</title><secondary-title>Chemosphere</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemosphere</full-title></periodical><pages>933-953</pages><volume>219</volume><keywords><keyword>Borneo</keyword><keyword>Geochemical speciation/fractionation</keyword><keyword>Lower Baram River</keyword><keyword>Risk assessment</keyword><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>Trace elements</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2019</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><accession-num>30572242</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemosphere.2018.11.158</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Prabakaran et al. 2019, Lower Baram River, Borneo, average bed sediment composition &amp; metal speciation.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The geochemistry and distribution of major, trace and rare earth elements (REE's) was studied in the surface sediments of the Lower Baram River during two seasons: the Monsoon (MON) and Post – monsoon (POM). The major geochemical processes controlling the distribution and mobility of major, trace and REE's in the Lower Baram River surface sediments was revealed through factor analysis. The risk assessment of major and trace element levels was studied at three specific levels; i.e. the enrichment level [Contamination Factor (Cf), with the geo-accumulation index (Igeo)], the availability level [metals bound to different fractions, risk assessment code (RAC)], and the biological toxicity level [effect range low (ERL) and effect range medium (ERM)]. The results of all the indices indicate that Cu is the element of concern in the Lower Baram River sediments. The geochemical fractionation of major and trace elements were studied through sequential extraction and the results indicated a higher concentration of Mn in the exchangeable fraction. The element of concern, Cu, was found to be highly associated in the organic bound (F4) fraction during both seasons and a change in the redox, possibly due to storms or dredging activities may stimulate the release of Cu into the overlying waters of the Lower Baram River.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Prohic, Esad</author><author>Juracic, Mladen</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Heavy Metals in Sediments - Problems Concerning Determination of the Anthropogenic Influence . Study in the Krka River Estuary , Eastern Adriatic Coast , Yugoslavia</title><secondary-title>Environ Geol Water Sci</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environ Geol Water Sci</full-title></periodical><pages>145-151</pages><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1989</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Prohic&amp;Juracic 1989, Krka River, Yugoslavia, Sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Put, Annick V A N</author><author>Grieken, Rent Van</author><author>Wilken, Rolf-drerer</author><author>Hudec, Barbara</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemical characterization of suspended matter and sediment samples from the Elbe river by EPXMA</title><secondary-title>Water Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Research</full-title></periodical><pages>643-655</pages><volume>28</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>--suspended matter</keyword><keyword>sediments</keyword><keyword>single particle analysis</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1994</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://vanput1994_ElbeRiverSPM Geochemical characterization.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Qiao, Shuqing</author><author>Yang, Zuosheng</author><author>Pan, Yanjun</author><author>Guo, Zhigang</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Metals in suspended sediments from the Changjiang (Yangtze River) and Huanghe (Yellow River) to the sea, and their comparison</title><secondary-title>Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Estuarine, Coastal and Shelf Science</full-title></periodical><pages>539-548</pages><volume>74</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Changjiang (Yangtze River)</keyword><keyword>Huanghe (Yellow River)</keyword><keyword>metals</keyword><keyword>sediment source</keyword><keyword>suspended sediments</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2007</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.ecss.2007.05.042</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://qiao2007_Yangtze+Huanghe river SPM comparison.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Thirty-five samples of suspended sediments were collected at Datong Station and Lijin Station, the basin-wide control stations of the Changjiang (Yangtze River) and the Huanghe (Yellow River) during flood and dry seasons in 2000 and 2001. Concentrations of 15 elements (Fe, Mg, Ca, Al, Na, K, Ti, Mn, Ba, Sr, Pb, Cu, Zn, V, and Ni) in these samples were measured by ICP-AES. The results indicated that Fe, Al, Ti, Mn, Ba, Cu, Zn, V and Ni concentrations in the Changjiang sediments in May (flood season) were quite close to those in November (dry season), whereas Mg, Ca, Na, K, Sr concentrations were slightly higher and Pb was relatively lower in the dry season. Ti, Ba, Sr and Zn concentrations in Huanghe sediments varied little in August (flood season) and December (dry season), while Mg, Ca, Al, Na and K concentrations were higher by approximately 30% and Fe, Mn, Pb, Cu, Zn, V and Ni concentrations were lower in flood season. Concentrations of most metals, except Ca, Na and Sr were much higher in Changjiang sediments than those in the Huanghe. Such differences of metal concentrations in sediments from these two rivers could be ascribed to their different sediment sources and weathering processes within their corresponding river basin. Particularly, since the 1980s, Pb and Zn concentrations in Changjiang sediments have increased significantly due to the releases of waste/contaminants from human activities, while the variations for these two elements in the Huanghe samples were very little due to the elevated river bed in the lower reaches. © 2007 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Qu, C. H.</author><author>Chen, C. Z.</author><author>Yang, J. R.</author><author>Wang, L. Z.</author><author>Lu, Y. L.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of dissolved and particulate elements in the major rivers of China (The Huanghe, Changjiang, and Zhunjiang rivers)</title><secondary-title>Estuaries</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Estuaries</full-title></periodical><pages>475-487</pages><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1993</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.2307/1352595</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Qu et al. 1993, Major Chinese Rivers aqueous and solid chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The relationship between the geochemistry of dissolved and particulate materials and geographic conditions was investigated. Samples of water and suspended particulate matter were collected from five locations in three of the major rivers of China (the Huanghe, Changjiang, and Zhunjiang rivers). Because these rivers generally flow parallel to latitudes and flow through diverse geologic and climate zones, they provide excellent opportunities for comparisons of solute transport. The geochemistry of these rivers is influenced strongly by climate. The low discharge of the Huanghe River influences the character of the major ionic materials (Cl−+SO42− and Na++K+) as well as the high degree of mineralization within the system. Dissolved concentrations of both major ions and trace elements are lower in the southern reaches of the rivers. The highly mobile ions, such as, Na+ and Ca2+, are depleted from the suspended particulate material in the southern regions, while the relatively immobile ions of Al, Fe, Ti, Mn, and trace metals are concentrated within the suspended mateiral. The relative mobility of some elements as measured by the Dissolved Transport Index (DTI) changes with climate. The geology of the area drained by the rivers has a major influence on the geochemistry in areas of similar climate. Lowest leaching rates in the southern climates occur in areas dominated by granite, which is resistant to weathering. The composition of both cations and anions among the three tributaries of the Zhujiang River are dependent on the rocks that dominate each eregion. Some particulate forms of the rare earth elements are present in the highest concentrations in regions dominated by granite. The DTI calculated for the major rivers in China are much smaller than those computed for other major rivers of the world. The low concentration of heavy metals in the particulate material suggests that pollution in the rivers of China is less serious than in rivers of other industrialized countries. © 1993, Estuarine Research Federation. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Book Section">7</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rachold, V.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Major, Trace and Rare Earth Element Geochemistry of Suspended Particulate Material of East Siberian Rivers Draining to the Arctic Ocean</title><secondary-title>Land-Ocean Systems in the Siberian Arctic</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Land-Ocean Systems in the Siberian Arctic</full-title></periodical><pages>199-222</pages><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/978-3-642-60134-7_20</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://rachold1999, East Siberian (Lena) River SPM Geochemistry (ME,TE,REE).pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rachold, V.</author><author>Alabyan, A.</author><author>Hubberten, H. W.</author><author>Korotaev, V. N.</author><author>Zaitsev, A. A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sediment transport to the Laptev Sea - Hydrology and geochemistry of the Lena River</title><secondary-title>Polar Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Polar Research</full-title></periodical><pages>183-196</pages><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1996</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1111/j.1751-8369.1996.tb00468.x</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Rachold et al. 1997_LenaRiver SPM and export to laptev sea.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study focuses on the fluvial sediment input to the Laptev Sea and concentrates on the hydrology of the Lena basin and the geochemistry of the suspended particulate material. The paper presents data on annual water discharge, sediment transport and seasonal variations of sediment transport. The data are based on daily measurements of hydrometeorological stations and additional analyses of the SPM concentrations carried out during expeditions from 1975 to 1981. Samples of the SPM collected during an expedition in 1994 were analysed for major, trace, and rare earth elements by ICP-OES and ICP-MS. Approximately 700 km3 freshwater and 27 × 106 tons of sediment per year are supplied to the Laptev Sea by Siberian rivers, mainly by the Lena River. Due to the climatic situation of the drainage area, almost the entire material is transported between June and September. However, only a minor part of the sediments transported by the Lena River enters the Laptev Sea shelf through the main channels of the delta, while the rest is dispersed within the network of the Lena Delta. Because the Lena River drains a large basin of 2.5 × 106 km2, the chemical composition of the SPM shows a very uniform composition. In contrast, smaller rivers with more restricted catchment areas exhibit significant differences.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rees, J. G.</author><author>Ridgway, J.</author><author>Knox, R. W.O.B.</author><author>Wiggans, G.</author><author>Breward, N.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sediment-borne contaminants in rivers discharging into the Humber Estuary, UK</title><secondary-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</full-title></periodical><pages>316-329</pages><volume>37</volume><issue>3-7</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0025-326X(99)00055-7</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Rees et al. 1998, Sediment discharging into Humber Bay, UK.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>As part of a project to characterise and quantify the volume of sediments which comprise the Holocene (10,000 years to present) fill of the Humber Estuary, a study was undertaken to determine the geochemistry and heavy mineralogy of bed sediments in the river systems that discharge into the estuary. A total of 19 sediment samples in the Trent and Ouse river systems were taken for analysis. Contamination was evaluated by comparison of the sample geochemistry with that of the appropriate catchment (using existing data), and by evaluation of the proportion of anthropogenic heavy minerals (including natural minerals which have been mobilised by mining) in the sediment sample. Heavy metals fall into two groups with different patterns of distribution. Pb-Zn concentrations are greatest in catchments and rivers draining the Pennine orefields. Levels of these metals remain high between source areas and the Humber Estuary suggesting that large quantities are trapped in sediments stored within the fluvial systems. By way of contrast other heavy metals, associated with manufacturing industry, such as Cu and Co, have high concentrations near source cities, but decrease rapidly in amount down the river systems because of dilution by other sediments. The differing behaviour of mining and industrial related contaminants is generally reflected by the heavy minerals. Concentrations of gangue minerals, such as barytes and fluorite, are generally highest in rivers draining mining areas; 'furnace' materials, such as slags are highest in industrialised rivers such as the Aire and the Don. The anthropogenic origin of all the contaminants is illustrated by comparison of the catchment and river sediment geochemistry and heavy mineralogy with that of early Holocene fluvially-derived sediments cored in boreholes drilled in the present Humber Estuary. The findings of the study corroborate those of others focused on water chemistry and floodplain sediments. However, the comparison of pre-existing data on catchment geochemistry with a limited number of river samples, as demonstrated here, provides a fast and cost effective tool for the determination of contamination characteristics in river systems.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Rousseau, Tristan C.C.</author><author>Roddaz, Martin</author><author>Moquet, Jean Sébastien</author><author>Handt Delgado, Helga</author><author>Calves, Gérôme</author><author>Bayon, Germain</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Controls on the geochemistry of suspended sediments from large tropical South American rivers (Amazon, Orinoco and Maroni)</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>38-54</pages><volume>522</volume><issue>May 2018</issue><keywords><keyword>Amazon River</keyword><keyword>Major and trace elements</keyword><keyword>Maroni River</keyword><keyword>Nd–Sr isotopes</keyword><keyword>Orinoco River</keyword><keyword>Suspended sediments</keyword><keyword>Yearly hydrological cycle</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2019</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2019.05.027</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://rousseau2019.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2019.05.027</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>We report mineralogical, elemental (major and trace elements) and Sr–Nd isotopic data for suspended particulate matter (SPM) samples from the Amazon, Orinoco and Maroni Rivers collected on a monthly basis over a one-year long hydrological cycle. The aim of this study was i) to characterize the mineralogical and geochemical composition of major South American tropical rivers and ii) to evaluate the effect of seasonal hydroclimate variations and changes in sediment discharge on the composition of these SPM. In addition to displaying particular mineralogical and geochemical signatures (e.g. Al/Si ratios, weathering indices), the Amazon, Orinoco and Maroni SPM are characterized by marked differences in 87Sr/86Sr (0.7213 ± 0.0030, 0.7288 ± 0.0018 and 0.7335 ± 0.0019, respectively), and εNd values (−10.6 ± 0.6, −14.1 ± 0.3 and −23.7 ± 1.2), which reflect differences in source rock lithology. While we find no effect of the hydrological cycle on the geochemistry of Orinoco SPM, particulate εNd and Cr/Th signatures fluctuate with the hydrological cycle in the Maroni basin, indicating that they are controlled by variation in rainfall distribution linked to the latitudinal migration of the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ). In contrast to Maroni and Orinoco SPM, the Amazon SPM are characterized by significant Sr isotope annual variability correlated with suspended sediments discharge and a small but significant Nd isotopic variability over the year. This latter variation is related to seasonal changes in the rainfall distribution patterns across the Amazon basin, associated with latitudinal migrations of the ITCZ. This suggests that the geochemical composition of the SPM exported over the year from the Amazon Basin faithfully responds to hydroclimate changes related associated with the migration of the rain belt over regions of contrasted geochemical signatures. These findings have implications for the application of Sr and Nd isotopes as provenance proxies in sedimentary archives and paleoclimatic studies. The Sr isotopic composition of exported SPM appears to be mostly controlled by weathering processes and/or mineralogical sorting, rather than being indicative of sediment provenance. In contrast, the relationship documented between Nd isotopes and the hydrological variability indicates that their application to archives of past river sediment discharges can provide unique insights on paleo-hydroclimate changes over tropical South America.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Roy, S.</author><author>Gaillardet, J.</author><author>Allègre, C. J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of dissolved and suspended loads of the Seine river, France: Anthropogenic impact, carbonate and silicate weathering</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>1277-1292</pages><volume>63</volume><issue>9</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0016-7037(99)00099-X</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Roy et al. 1999, Seine river diss and susp load.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study focuses on the chemistry of the Seine river system, one of the major rivers in Europe, and constitutes the first geochemical investigation of both suspended and dissolved loads of this river. The Seine river drains a typical Mesozoic-Cenozoic sedimentary basin: the Paris basin, constituted of limestones mixed or interbedded with terrigenous sediments derived from the paleoreliefs bordering the Mesozoic and Cenozoic seas. In the context of quantifying the global influence of carbonate and silicate weathering on atmospheric CO2 consumption, the Seine river offers the possibility of examining weathering rates in a flat sedimentary environment, under temperate climatic conditions. One of the major problems associated with the Seine river, as with many temperate rivers, is pollution. We propose, in this paper, 2 approaches in order to correct the dissolved load of the Seine river for anthropogenic inputs and to calculate weathering rates of carbonates and silicates. The first uses the dissolved load of rivers and tries to allocate the different solutes to different sources. A mixing model, based on elemental ratios, is established and solved by an inversion technique. The second approach consists in using the suspended load geochemistry. Under steady state conditions, we show that the geochemistry of suspended sediments makes it possible to estimate the amount of solutes released during the chemical weathering of silicates, and thus to calculate weathering rates of silicates. The total dissolved load of the Seine river at Paris can be decomposed into 2% of solutes derived from natural atmospheric sources, 7% derived from anthropogenic atmospheric sources, 6% derived from agriculture, 3% derived from communal inputs, and 82% of solutes derived from rock weathering. During high floods, the contribution of atmospheric and agriculture inputs predominates. The weathering rate of carbonates is estimated to be 48 t/km2/yr (25 mm/1000 yr). Only 10% of carbonates are transported in a solid form, the rest being transported in solution. CO2 consumption by carbonate weathering approaches 400 X 103 mol/km2/yr. In the Seine river at Paris, about 2-3 mg/l of dissolved cations are found to originate from the chemical wheathering of silicates. By taking dissolved silica into accounts, the total dissolved load derived from silicate weathering is about 6-7 mg/l. This value is minimal because biological uptake of silica probably occur in the Seine river. The chemical weathering rate of aluminosilicates is estimated to be 2 t/km2/yr. The ratio of physical over chemical weathering of silicates range between 1 and 3 and the total (chemical and physical) erosion rates of sedimentary silicates are about 2-3 mm/kyr. The CO2 consumption by silicate weathering 15-24 X 103 mol/km2/yr and is independent of dissolved silica concentration. Silicate consumption is thus 20 times less than carbonate consumption in the Paris basin. Compared to the neighboring granitic areas, the sedimentary region drained by the Seine river has 2 to 3 times lower CO2 consumption rates. We attribute this difference to the cation-depleted nature of the Seine basin aluminosilicates, which are of sedimentary origin. At a world scale, the chemical denudation rates found for the Seine basin are very low and comparable to those given for tropical lowland rivers draining silicates. such as the rivers of the Congo and Amazon basins, in spite of huge climatic differences. We attribute this similarity to the low mechanical denudation that characterizes these two types of regions.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Ruiz, E.</author><author>Romero, F.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Composition of torrential river sediments from Ne of Spain</title><secondary-title>Toxicological &amp; Environmental Chemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Toxicological &amp; Environmental Chemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>191-201</pages><volume>52</volume><issue>1-4</issue><keywords><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>heavy metals</keyword><keyword>sediment analysis</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1995</year></dates><isbn>0277224950</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1080/02772249509358260</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://ruiz &amp; romero 1995, small basque rivers sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The composition of sediment samples from the rivers Lea, Oria and Bidasoa (NE of Spain) has been determined by analytical procedures (AAS and HA) and size fraction analysis. Measured parameters include major (organic carbon, Cationic exchange capacity, carbonates, Na, K, Ca, Mg, Si, Al and Fe) and microconstituents (Cu, Zn, Mn, Pb, Ni, Cr and Cd). Results for total and fine (&lt; 63 microns) samples are discussed by conventional and multivariate (factor and cluster analyses) statistical techniques. © 1995, Taylor &amp; Francis Group, LLC. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Salomons, W.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Chemical and isotopic composition of carbonates in recent sediments and soils from western Europe</title><secondary-title>Journal of Sedimentary Petrology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Sedimentary Petrology</full-title></periodical><pages>440-449</pages><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>icle</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1975</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Salomons 1975, Rhine-Meuse-Ems-Scheldt-Somme-Seine Carbonate content &amp; Sr 13C.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Sindern, Sven</author><author>Tremöhlen, Martin</author><author>Dsikowitzky, Larissa</author><author>Gronen, Lars</author><author>Schwarzbauer, Jan</author><author>Siregar, Tuti Hartati</author><author>Ariyani, Farida</author><author>Irianto, Hari Eko</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Heavy metals in river and coast sediments of the Jakarta Bay region (Indonesia) — Geogenic versus anthropogenic sources</title><secondary-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine Pollution Bulletin</full-title></periodical><pages>624-633</pages><volume>110</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Coastal megacity</keyword><keyword>Heavy metals</keyword><keyword>Indonesia</keyword><keyword>Jakarta</keyword><keyword>River sediment</keyword><keyword>Tropical coastal ecosystem</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2016</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier Ltd</publisher><accession-num>27293077</accession-num><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.06.003</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Sindern et al. 2016, Jakarta Bay, Indonesia, river and coast sediment chemistry and mineralogy.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.marpolbul.2016.06.003</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>Sediment geochemistry of the Jakarta region, a densely populated tropical coast, is studied — with particular focus on rivers discharging to Jakarta Bay. Weathering volcanics in the river catchment area control the composition of major elements, As, Cr and in part Cu. In contrast, Zn, Ni, Pb and partly Cu are affected by anthropogenic sources, mainly in central Jakarta City. The data reflect a high variability of local emission sources, among which metal processing industries, fertilizers or untreated animal waste may be important. In particular, the role of street dusts is emphasized. Locally, heavy metals reach levels considered to have adverse biological effects. River discharge leads to anthropogenic enrichment of heavy metals in the coastal sediments. Element data also show geogenic effects on the composition of the coastal sediments, such as mixing of detrital silicates with biogenic carbonates as well as suspended particulate matter from the ocean.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Singh, A. K.</author><author>Hasnain, S. I.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Environmental geochemistry of Damodar River basin, east coast of India</title><secondary-title>Environmental Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environmental Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>124-136</pages><volume>37</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Anthropogenic</keyword><keyword>Damodar River</keyword><keyword>Heavy metal</keyword><keyword>TOtal suspended matter</keyword><keyword>Total dissolved solids</keyword><keyword>Weathering</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1999</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s002540050369</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Singh &amp; Hasnain1999_Damodar River, India, sediment and aqueous chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Water and bed sediment samples collected from the Damodar River and its tributaries were analysed to study elemental chemistry and suspended load characteristics of the river basin. Na and ca are the dominant cations and HCO3 is the dominant anion. The water chemistry of the Damodar River basin strongly reflects the dominance of continental weathering aided by atmospheric and anthropogenic activities in the catchment area. High concentrations of SO4 and PO4 at some sites indicate the mining and anthropogenic impact on writer quality. The high concentration of dissolved silica, relatively high (Na + K)/TZ+ ratio (0.2-0.4) and low equivalent ratio of (Ca + Mg)/(Na +K) indicate that dissolved ions contribute significantly to the weathering of aluminosilicate minerals of crystalline rocks. The seasonal data show a minimum ionic concentration in the monsoon season, reflecting the influence of atmospheric precipitation on total dissolved solids contents. The suspended sediments show a positive correlation with discharge and both discharge and suspended load reach their maximum value during the monsoon season. Kaolinite is the mineral that is possibly in equilibrium with the water. This implies that the chemistry of the Damodar River water favours kaolinite formation. The concentration of heavy metals in the finer size fraction (&lt; 37 μ m) is significantly higher than the bulk composition. The geoaccumulation index values calculated for Fe, Mn, Zn, Ni and Cr are well below zero, suggesting that there is no pollution from these metals in Damodar River sediments.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Sorokina, O. A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Chemical composition of the Zeya River sediments in weathering trend of river sediments of Asia</title><secondary-title>Environmental Earth Sciences</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environmental Earth Sciences</full-title></periodical><pages>1-10</pages><volume>79</volume><issue>1</issue><keywords><keyword>CIA</keyword><keyword>CIW</keyword><keyword>PIA</keyword><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>V</keyword><keyword>WIP</keyword><keyword>Weathering</keyword><keyword>Zeya River</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year></dates><publisher>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher><isbn>0123456789</isbn><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s12665-019-8686-1</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Sorokina2020_Zeya River, Amur Trib, bottom sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls><web-urls><url>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12665-019-8686-1</url></web-urls></urls><abstract>The chemical composition of river sediments reflects bedrock geochemistry in the area of erosion and characterizes trend of weathering in the catchment area. The article presents data about chemical composition of Zeya River sediments. This river is one of the largest watercourses in the Amur River basin. The chemical composition of river sediments was analyzed by X-ray fluorescence spectrometry. Compared with the upper continental crust, the river sediments are depleted in almost all analyzed major elements. According to the analysis of major element the ratio, degree of weathering of river sediments in Middle Reach of the Zeya increases down the river. The chemical composition of studied river sediments is close to those in the rivers of northeastern China.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Sorokina, O. A.</author><author>Zarubina, N. V.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Chemical composition of the bottom sediments in the middle reaches of the Amur River</title><secondary-title>Russian Journal of Pacific Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Russian Journal of Pacific Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>469-476</pages><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><keywords><keyword>Amur River</keyword><keyword>bottom deposits</keyword><keyword>multielement diagrams</keyword><keyword>rare-earth elements</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2011</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1134/S1819714011050095</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Sorokina &amp; Zarubina 2011, Amur River, Bottom Sediment Composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The chemical composition of the bottom sediments of the Amur River has been analyzed using modern analytical techniques. It was found that their composition and distribution patterns are controlled by several sources. The most probable sources for the bottom sediments of the studied area are siliceous magmatic or metasedimentary rocks. © 2011 Pleiades Publishing, Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Sorokina, O. A.</author><author>Zarubina, N. V.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The content of chemical elements in alluvial soils and bottom sediments of the Urkan River (the Amur River basin)</title><secondary-title>Eurasian Soil Science</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Eurasian Soil Science</full-title></periodical><pages>644-653</pages><volume>46</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords><keyword>chemical composition</keyword><keyword>river systems</keyword><keyword>the Far East</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1134/S1064229313060094</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Sorokina &amp; Zarubina 2013, Urkan River Bottom Sediment composition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The distribution patterns of the chemical elements in the bottom sediments and alluvial soils of the Urkan River valley (one of the largest tributaries of the Zeya River, a tributary of the Amur River) have been examined. It is shown that the concentrations of the chemical elements in the bottom sediments generally correspond to those in the bedrocks composing the river catchment and in the upper part of the continental earth's crust, though the accumulation of most of the elements in the bottom sediments is somewhat lower. The composition of the microelements in the alluvial soils is mainly determined by the composition of the microelements in the bottom sediments. The alluvial soils are somewhat enriched in Mn, Zn, Co, and Cu, which is related to the biological accumulation of these elements entering the trophic chains. © 2013 Pleiades Publishing, Ltd.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Report">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Stirton, Daniel</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Quantifying Transport of Particulate Inorganic Carbon in the Madre de Dios River</title></titles><periodical/><pages>1-24</pages><keywords/><dates><year>2016</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Stirton_PIC-Thesis_2016.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Striegl, Robert G.</author><author>Dornblaser, Mark M.</author><author>Aiken, George R.</author><author>Wickland, Kimberly P.</author><author>Raymond, Peter A.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Carbon export and cycling by the Yukon, Tanana, and Porcupine rivers, Alaska, 2001-2005</title><secondary-title>Water Resources Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Resources Research</full-title></periodical><volume>43</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2007</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1029/2006WR005201</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Striegl et al. 2007, Yukon river Carbon cycle.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Loads and yields of dissolved and particulate organic and inorganic carbon (DOC, POC, DIC, PIC) were measured and modeled at three locations on the Yukon River (YR) and on the Tanana and Porcupine rivers (TR, PR) in Alaska during 2001-2005. Total YR carbon export averaged 7.8 Tg C yr-1, 30% as OC and 70% as IC. Total C yields (0.39-1.03 mol C m-2 yr-1) were proportional to water yields (139-356 mm yr-1; r2 = 0.84) at all locations. Summer DOC had an aged component (fraction modern (FM) = 0.94-0.97), except in the permafrost wetland-dominated PR, where DOC was modern. POC had FM = 0.63-0.70. DOC had high concentration, high aromaticity, and high hydrophobic content in spring and low concentration, low aromaticity, and high hydrophilic content in winter. About half of annual DOC export occurred during spring. DIC concentration and isotopic composition were strongly affected by dissolution of suspended carbonates in glacial meltwater during summer.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Subramanian, V.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Mineralogical input of suspended matter by Indian rivers into the adjacent areas of the Indian ocean</title><secondary-title>Marine Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>29-34</pages><volume>36</volume><keywords/><dates><year>1980</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://subramanian1980_IndianRivers DrainingIndian Ocean SPM mineralogy.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Subramanian, V.</author><author>van t' Dack, L.</author><author>van Grieken, R.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Preliminary studies on the geochemistry of the Cauvery river basin</title><secondary-title>Proceedings of the Indian Academy of Sciences - Earth and Planetary Sciences</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Proceedings of the Indian Academy of Sciences - Earth and Planetary Sciences</full-title></periodical><pages>99-110</pages><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><keywords><keyword>Cauvery river basin</keyword><keyword>Geochemistry</keyword><keyword>annual erosion rates</keyword><keyword>co-genetic behaviour</keyword><keyword>sediment load</keyword><keyword>x-ray fluorescence</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1985</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/BF02871942</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Subramanian1985_GeochemistryCauveryRvrBasin.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Samples of water and sediments were collected over a three year period from the entire region of Cauvery river basin excluding the estuary. On the basis of our observations, we have calculated the average composition of the Cauvery river at several locations from the catchment to the river mouth, the downstream profile of sediment load, annual erosion rates, solute and sediment fluxes and have predicted on long term changes. The sediment chemistry was determined by x-ray fluorescence (xrf) technique, and calculated mean compositions of the Cauvery and its tributary bed and the suspended sediment were compared to those of world average river sediments. Downstream profiles of some of the elements appear to be controlled by size and mineralogical characteristics besides local factors specific to the location of the samples. Interelemental relationships indicated good correlation among the transition elements indicating their co-genetic behaviour within the drainage basin. © 1985 Indian Academy of Sciences.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Subramanian, V.</author><author>Van 't Dack, L.</author><author>Van Grieken, R.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Chemical composition of river sediments from the Indian sub-continent</title><secondary-title>Chemical Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Chemical Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>271-279</pages><volume>48</volume><issue>1-4</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1985</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/0009-2541(85)90052-X</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Subramanian et al. 1985b, Indian River Chemistry draining to ocean.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>River sediments from all of the major drainage basins (except the Indus) in the Indian sub-continent were collected and analysed by thin-film X-ray fluorescence technique (XRF) to determine their chemical composition. On the basis of analysis of more than 120 samples, average chemical compositions of river-borne sediments from the Indian sub-continent have been calculated. Also, average concentration values for sediments from each of the river basins, and the sub-continent average and the inter-basin differences are discussed in relation to weathering processes in the drainage basins. Comparisons have been made with the chemistry of sediments from the Bay of Bengal (which receives the bulk of sediments delivered by Indian rivers). Our observations are discussed in the light of average chemical composition of world-river sediments and the world surface rock exposed for continental weathering. © 1985.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Tesi, T.</author><author>Miserocchi, S.</author><author>Acri, F.</author><author>Langone, L.</author><author>Boldrin, A.</author><author>Hatten, J. A.</author><author>Albertazzi, S.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Flood-driven transport of sediment, particulate organic matter, and nutrients from the Po River watershed to the Mediterranean Sea</title><secondary-title>Journal of Hydrology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Hydrology</full-title></periodical><pages>144-152</pages><volume>498</volume><keywords><keyword>Flood</keyword><keyword>Mediterranean watershed</keyword><keyword>Nutrients</keyword><keyword>Organic matter</keyword><keyword>Po River</keyword><keyword>Sediment transport</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2013</year></dates><publisher>Elsevier B.V.</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.jhydrol.2013.06.001</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://tesi2013_Italy,PoRiver SPM PIC.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The Po River (Northern Italy) discharge represents a considerable input of the land-derived material entering the Mediterranean Sea. Most of its particulate and dissolved constituents are supplied to the sea in response to short-lived climate events. Although these floods exert first-order control on the transport of organic and inorganic elements, both composition and magnitude of the river material are poorly constrained during high discharge periods. In order to fill this knowledge gap, in this study we carried out an event response sampling in the Po River in November 2011. Beginning in early November, intense rainfall occurred in the Po watershed that resulted in a flood of ~6000m3s-1 (2.5year return period). Water samples were collected from the river before and during the flood. Dissolved nitrate, nitrite, ammonia, and silicate were measured and the particulate material was analyzed for total suspended sediment, elemental composition, δ13C, δ15N, grain-size, and 137Cs activity.Our results showed a temporal decoupling between solid and water discharge implying that predicted sediment loads simply derived from sediment rating curves could potentially give rise to large errors, especially when calculations are used to understand the sediment export in response short-lived events. The suspended organic material during high flow was dominated by soil organic matter while high δ15N indicated the influence of an additional 15N-enriched source (e.g., manure, sewage, and algal biomass) during low discharge. Because the concentrations of nitrite and ammonia were positively correlated with the content of particulate material in suspension, we inferred that nitrite and ammonia concentrations were driven by either bacteria activity (ammonification-nitrification) or ionic exchange whose rates were proportional to concentration of the suspended material. In addition, due to the dilution with nitrate-poor rainfall, the concentration of nitrate decreased with increasing water discharge. High concentrations of nitrate were instead attributable to the influx of nitrate-rich water from groundwater that is chronically contaminated and constitutes most of the baseflow during low flow. Our results indicate that the event-dominated transport in the Po drainage basin is particularly important for the organic matter supply as flood events account for at least one-third of the particulate annual export (organic carbon and nitrogen). Finally, this study has demonstrated the utility of event-response sampling for understanding the importance of event-dominated transport in rivers. © 2013 Elsevier B.V.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Thorpe, Michael T.</author><author>Hurowitz, Joel A.</author><author>Dehouck, Erwin</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sediment geochemistry and mineralogy from a glacial terrain river system in southwest Iceland</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>140-166</pages><volume>263</volume><keywords><keyword>basaltic terrains</keyword><keyword>river sediments</keyword><keyword>sedimentation</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2019</year></dates><publisher>The Author(s)</publisher><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.gca.2019.08.003</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Thorpe et al. 2019, SW Iceland SPM mineralogy and chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The weathering of basalt has implications for the global carbon cycle on Earth as well as for understanding sedimentary processes on other terrestrial bodies dominated by a basaltic crust (e.g., Mars), but yet studies in mafic terrains are limited in comparison to their felsic counterpart. Our work details the compositional transformations resulting from the sedimentation process of first-cycle sediments generated in a basalt dominated watershed of southwest Iceland. By sampling multiple sites along the Hvítá S river transport pathway and analyzing the sedimentology, geochemistry, and mineralogy, this work provides a geologically integrated approach to understanding a fluvial source-to-sink system in mafic terrains. Environmental conditions such as climate, hydrology, and transport distance all influence the overall sediment composition, and in response, chemical weathering, physical abrasion, sorting, transport, and mixing are all sedimentary processes unraveled in the geochemical and mineralogical relationships of individual grain size bins. Chemical weathering initiates in the upper reaches of the watershed with the alteration of primary mafic phases to form secondary weathering products. As sediment continues to move downstream, the entire sediment suite becomes more altered, and the extent of chemical weathering is intensified, as evidenced by a higher abundance of clay minerals and glassy material. Fluvial sorting separates detritus by particle size and differentiates them by compositional gradients in geochemistry and mineralogy. As grain size decreases, mafic minerals become less abundant and the finer grain sizes are preferentially enriched in immature weathering minerals and mineraloids (e.g., smectite clays and X-ray amorphous phases). This grain size trend is also correlated with elemental fractionation, illustrated most notably by the clay size fraction (&lt;2 μm) hosting the most altered material in river sediments. However, we note that the environmental conditions of Iceland (e.g., a cold climate and glacial reworking) result in limited element mobility when compared to more temperate climates around the world. Therefore, we suggest that the clay size fraction of river sediments provide a valuable target for understanding the intensity of weathering in these systems, particularly in a colder climate where mineralogical transformations are not always accompanied by a high degree of elemental loss. In addition to weathering and sorting, trace element abundances suggest the mixing of sediments from varying provenances. While the Hvítá S watershed is dominated by basalt, even minor amounts of evolved volcanics (e.g., andesites) contribute to the overall sediment composition. Overall, this work fills a knowledge gap in sedimentation processes in basaltic terrains on Earth, while additionally providing a valuable terrestrial analog for ancient fluvial-deltaic environments preserved in the sedimentary rock record of Mars (e.g., Gale Crater and Jezero Crater).</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Report">10</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Trefry, John H</author><author>Rember, Robert D</author><author>Trocine, Robert P.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Sources , Concentrations and Dispersion Pathways for Suspended Sediment in the Coastal Beaufort Sea Final Report Submitted to Suspended Sediment in the Coastal Beaufort Sea</title><secondary-title>U.S. Department of Interior Minerals Management Service Anchorage, Alaska</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>U.S. Department of Interior Minerals Management Service Anchorage, Alaska</full-title></periodical><pages>84</pages><issue>143501</issue><keywords/><dates><year>2004</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Trefry et al. 2004, Alaska River SPM and marine sediments.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Vale, C</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Transport of particulate metals at different fluvial and tidal energies in the Tagus River estuary</title><secondary-title>Rapports (Process Verbal) des Réunions du Conseil international pour l'Exploration de la Mer Méditerranée</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Rapports (Process Verbal) des Réunions du Conseil international pour l'Exploration de la Mer Méditerranée</full-title></periodical><pages>306-312</pages><volume>186</volume><keywords><keyword>discharge</keyword><keyword>estuaries</keyword><keyword>hydrodynamics</keyword><keyword>metals</keyword><keyword>pollution</keyword><keyword>portugl, tagus river estuary</keyword><keyword>sediment transport</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1986</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Vale 1986, Tagus river, Spain, SPM composition annual &amp; flood.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>van der Perk, Marcel</author><author>Vilches, Alvaro Espinoza</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Compositional dynamics of suspended sediment in the Rhine River: sources and controls</title><secondary-title>Journal of Soils and Sediments</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Journal of Soils and Sediments</full-title></periodical><pages>1754-1770</pages><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><keywords><keyword>Concentration-discharge relationships</keyword><keyword>Principal component analysis</keyword><keyword>Rare earth elements</keyword><keyword>Suspended sediment</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2020</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s11368-019-02490-5</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Perk-Vilches2020_Rhine at Lobith_CompositionalDynamicsOfSuspend.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Purpose: Information on the geochemical composition of suspended sediments in rivers is crucial to identify sediment source type or area. In large river basins, however, the relation between sediment composition and its controlling factors is often obscured. This study aims to assess and improve the conceptual understanding on the factors and mechanisms that control the composition of suspended sediments in the River Rhine, one of the large European rivers, and to identify the dominant source types of elements. Materials and methods: We performed log-linear regression analysis and principal component analysis (PCA) on bi-weekly monitoring data of suspended sediment composition, supplemented with daily measurements of suspended sediment concentrations (SSC) and discharge at the Lobith monitoring station near the German-Dutch border for the period 2011–2016. Results and discussion: The statistical analyses show a consistent grouping of elements that display contrasting temporal variation or different responses to increased discharge. The contrasting behaviour also becomes manifest in the results from the PCA. A first component that explains about the half of the total variance in the entire dataset reflects the variation in clay content in the suspended sediment. A second component reflects anthropogenic pollution and explains about a quarter of the total variance. A third component probably reflects variation in sediment provenance. Conclusions: The majority of the temporal variation in suspended sediment composition can be attributed to variations in grain size (clay content), organic matter content, and anthropogenic pollution. Only a minority of the variation can be attributed to variations in the contributions from different upstream source areas. This variation represented by the third and higher components from the PCA can potentially be used for sediment provenance analysis.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Viers, Jérôme</author><author>Roddaz, Martin</author><author>Filizola, Naziano</author><author>Guyot, Jean Loup</author><author>Sondag, Francis</author><author>Brunet, Pierre</author><author>Zouiten, Cyril</author><author>Boucayrand, Carole</author><author>Martin, François</author><author>Boaventura, Géraldo Resende</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Seasonal and provenance controls on Nd-Sr isotopic compositions of Amazon rivers suspended sediments and implications for Nd and Sr fluxes exported to the Atlantic Ocean</title><secondary-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</full-title></periodical><pages>511-523</pages><volume>274</volume><issue>3-4</issue><keywords><keyword>Amazon River</keyword><keyword>Nd-Sr isotopic composition</keyword><keyword>erosion</keyword><keyword>flux</keyword><keyword>suspended sediment</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2008</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.epsl.2008.08.011</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Viers et al. 2008, Amazon river SPM composition and export to Atlantic.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>This study reports daily water discharge and suspended sediment load concentrations and Sm-Nd and Rb-Sr isotopic systematics and major and trace elements concentrations of twelve monthly sampled suspended load sediments of the Solimões and Madeira rivers, the two major Andean tributaries of the Amazon, during the year 2004. As observed in other long-term monitoring studies of Amazon Rivers, the maximum of suspended sediment load occurs before or during the rising water period (i.e. during the rainy season). In 2004, the Solimões River exported ∼ 289 × 106 tonnes of suspended sediments and the Madeira River 294 × 106 tonnes which correspond to erosion rates of 129 and 214 T/km2/yr for the Solimoes and Madeira rivers basins, respectively. Both the Solimoes and Madeira suspended sediments are enriched in LREE over HREE and exhibit similar MREE enrichment; the difference being that the Madeira sediments are more fractionated than the Solimoes ones. When plotted in Al2O3-CaO + Na2O-K2O diagram, the suspended sediments of the Solimoes and Madeira rivers exhibit two different weathering trends which suggests that these sediments evolved along two different trends starting from felsic rocks with different chemical compositions. The Nd isotopic compositions (εNd) of the Solimoes sediments (- 8.9 to 9.9) are slightly more radiogenic than the corresponding values of the Madeira sediments (- 10.8 to - 12.1). The 87Sr/86Sr isotopic compositions of the Madeira sediments (0.728 to 0.740) are significantly more radiogenic than those of the Solimoes (0.713 to 0.717). Together with other major elements and REE evidences, these isotopic compositions suggest that the Solimoes sediments are more influenced by Andean volcanic arc detritus than the Madeira sediments that might be due to input of young basaltic products owing to strong volcanic activity in Ecuador. Mineralogical compositions as well as Nd isotopic compositions do not vary seasonally. Based on our data set and on previous published studies, we have calculated that the Nd suspended sediment flux dominates the Nd total flux (i.e., dissolved + suspended sediment) exported to the Atlantic Ocean by the Amazon River representing ∼ 98% of the Nd total flux and having a global εNd isotopic composition of - 10.3. Contrary to Nd isotopic compositions, Sr isotopic compositions vary seasonally in both rivers. The explanation for this variation remains unclear. We suspect increasing physical weathering during the rainy season to be the main cause of this seasonal control in favouring landslides and river bank erosion that might induce input of more radiogenic sediments not easily mobilized during low water level. We calculated that the Sr isotopic composition of the dissolved load exported by the Amazon River to the Atlantic Ocean is not seasonally dependent and remain fairly constant (0.715-0.716) By contrast, the Sr isotopic composition of the suspended load is strongly affected by the seasonal variation varying from 0.714 in the dry season to 0.730 in the rainy season. Consequently the total Sr isotopic composition (dissolved + suspended sediment) is also seasonally controlled varying from 0.716 to 0.722. We finally suggest that large seasonally controlled Sr isotopic variations of great river is a phenomenon that has been underestimated in previous paleo-climatic and paleo-oceanic studies and should be taken into account in further studies. © 2008 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Wagemann, R.</author><author>Brunskill, G. J.</author><author>Graham, B. W.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Composition and reactivity of some river sediments from the Mackenzie Valley, N.W.T., Canada</title><secondary-title>Environmental Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Environmental Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>349-358</pages><volume>1</volume><issue>6</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1977</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1007/BF02380503</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://wagemann1977_Mackenzie River, Canada, East Channel Delta and SPM.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Sediments from the Mackenzie Valley - two suspended and one river bottom - were analyzed for major and minor elements, mineralogy, particle size, and ability to release trace metals when subjected to mild leaching. Copper and zinc in suspended sediments and cadmium in bottom sediment occurred largely (70 to 84 percent for Cu, 72 to 98 percent for Zn, 75 to 81 percent for Cd) in a form that could not easily be separated from the sediments by 0.1M HC1 and EDTA solutions. Cadmium was present in suspended sediments in low concentrations, and was present totally in sorbed leachable form. Iron, manganese, cobalt and chromium were separable from the particulate phase by mild leaching. It was found that approximately 70 hours were required for an apparent steady state concentration to be attained in such leachings. Reaction of these sediments with Beaufort Sea water (salinity 22.3 parts per thousand) indicated that both iron and manganese were released from sediments to sea water to a very small degree. Copper, lead, and zinc, however, were absorbed by sediments from sea water. © 1977 Springer-Verlag New York Inc.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Wei Wen Huang</author><author>Jing, Zhang</author><author>Zeng Hao Zhou</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Particulate element inventory of the Huanghe (Yellow River): A large, high-turbidity river</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>3669-3680</pages><volume>56</volume><issue>10</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1992</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/0016-7037(92)90160-K</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://huang1992_Huanghe, China, SPM chemistry+mineralogy+loess.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Suspended sediments from the river mouth to the upper portions of the Huanghe (Yellow River) were collected and analysed to determine their chemical composition. Comparison with other large world rivers indicates that trace element levels are relatively low in this high-turbidity river. Natural weathering and erosion are of primary importance in controlling particulate element concentrations, although the impact from anthropogenic activities is also visible. Finally, input of particulate elements to the China Sea is assessed from the river sediment load and compositions. © 1992.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Weijden, C H V A N D E R</author><author>Middelburg, J J</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Hydrogeochemistry of the river rhine: long term a n d seasonal variability, elemental budgets, base levels a n d pollution</title><secondary-title>Water Research</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Water Research</full-title></periodical><pages>1247-1266</pages><volume>23</volume><issue>10</issue><keywords><keyword>--hydrogeochemistry</keyword><keyword>elements</keyword><keyword>rhine</keyword><keyword>time series</keyword></keywords><dates><year>1989</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://vanderWeijdenMiddelburg89_RhineSPMComposition.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Yang, S. Y.</author><author>Li, C. X.</author><author>Jung, H. S.</author><author>Lee, H. J.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Discrimination of geochemical compositions between the Changjiang and the Huanghe sediments and its application for the identification of sediment source in the Jiangsu coastal plain, China</title><secondary-title>Marine Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>229-241</pages><volume>186</volume><issue>3-4</issue><keywords><keyword>Changjiang</keyword><keyword>Coastal plain</keyword><keyword>Geochemical composition</keyword><keyword>Huanghe</keyword><keyword>Sediment source</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2002</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/S0025-3227(02)00335-3</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Yang et al. 2002, Changjiand &amp; Huanghe, sediment characterization and contributions to marine sedimentation.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>Concentrations of 25 elements in the fine-grained fraction (&lt; 63 μm) of bottom sediments of the Changjiang and the Huanghe were determined to characterize the geochemical compositions of each riverine origin. Most of the elements, except for alkali and alkaline earth elements (Na, Ca, Sr and Bay), are highly enriched in the Changjiang sediments compared to those in the Huanghe sediments. Differences in source rocks and weathering mechanisms between the two drainage basins are the major factors controlling those compositional characteristics. The provenance index of core sediments from the northern Jiangsu coastal plain, calculated with nine elements with distinct compositional differences between both river sediments, indicates that the Changjiang had prevailed in the coastal plain sedimentation during the early stage of Holocene, while the Huanghe dominated over the area during the late Holocene, However, neither of the signatures of the modern Changjiang- and Huanghe-derived sediments is remarkable in the present-day coastal plain. © 2002 Elsevier Science B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Yang, Shouye</author><author>Jung, Hoi Soo</author><author>Li, Congxian</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Two unique weathering regimes in the Changjiang and Huanghe drainage basins: Geochemical evidence from river sediments</title><secondary-title>Sedimentary Geology</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Sedimentary Geology</full-title></periodical><pages>19-34</pages><volume>164</volume><issue>1-2</issue><keywords><keyword>Changjiang and Huanghe</keyword><keyword>Geochemistry</keyword><keyword>River sediments</keyword><keyword>Silicate weathering</keyword></keywords><dates><year>2004</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/j.sedgeo.2003.08.001</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Yang et al. 2004, Changjiang &amp; Huanghe sediment composition lower course.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The present research reconstructs the histories of chemical weathering in the drainage basins of the Changjiang and Huanghe based on the chemical compositions of the river sediments. The silicate weathering of the Changjiang Basin is strong and Na- and Ca-silicate minerals are considerably dissolved, while other silicate minerals are less attacked. In comparison, the Huanghe Basin is characterized by very weak silicate weathering, and the weathering degree corresponds well with that of the loess which is the predominant source of the Huanghe sediment. Overall, the Changjiang and Huanghe basins constitute a consistent weathering spectrum from the early to intermediate stage. The similarity of chemical compositions between upper continental crust and the Huanghe sediments as well as the low degree of chemical weathering in the Huanghe Basin imply that the river sediments can be considered to be the representative of UCC and are suitable for studying the evolution of continental crust. Our observations indicate that climate is the predominant factor controlling silicate weathering in both river basins, while controls by source rocks and relief are subordinate. Highly erosive river basins such as the Huanghe produce poorly weathered materials, which casts doubt on the idea that strong physical weathering naturally contributes much to chemical weathering. Differences in silicate weathering processes between the Changjiang and Huanghe basins may provide more constraints in estimating atmospheric CO2 budget in China. © 2003 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Yuan-Hui, Li</author><author>Teraoka, Hisayuki</author><author>Tsuo-Sheng, Yang</author><author>Jing-Sheng, Chen</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The elemental composition of suspended particles from the Yellow and Yangtze Rivers</title><secondary-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</full-title></periodical><pages>1561-1564</pages><volume>48</volume><issue>7</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1984</year></dates><electronic-resource-num>10.1016/0016-7037(84)90411-3</electronic-resource-num><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Yuan-Hui 1984, Yellow and Yangtze river SPM chemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls><abstract>The elemental composition of suspended particles from the Yellow River is similar to those of the loess terraces and the world's average soils. The contents of Zn, Cu, Ni, Co and Pb in the suspended particles are higher in the Yangtze River than in the Yellow River, indicating pollution inputs or the high-side of natural variability. © 1984.</abstract></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Z., Borovec</author><author>Mráz, L.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>The Character of the Fine Fractions of the Bottom Sediments of the Bohemian Part of the Labe (Elbe) River</title><secondary-title>Geo-Journal</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Geo-Journal</full-title></periodical><pages>371-378</pages><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><keywords/><dates><year>1992</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Borovec et al. Upr Elbe, Czech Rep, Sediment mineralogy.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record><record><database name="References_RiSCom.enl" path="References_RiSCom.enl">References_RiSCom.enl</database><ref-type name="Journal Article">0</ref-type><contributors><authors><author>Zwolsman, John J.G.</author><author>van Eck, Gijsbertus T.M.</author></authors></contributors><titles><title>Geochemistry of major elements and trace metals in suspended matter of the Scheldt estuary, southwest Netherlands</title><secondary-title>Marine ChemistryMarine Chemistry</secondary-title></titles><periodical><full-title>Marine ChemistryMarine Chemistry</full-title></periodical><pages>91-111</pages><volume>66</volume><keywords/><dates><year>1999</year></dates><urls><pdf-urls><url>internal-pdf://Zwolsman &amp; van Eck 1999, Scheld estuary SPM geochemistry.pdf</url></pdf-urls></urls></record></records></xml>
